
    <document>
        <title>Plaintiff United States'
Explanation of Consent Decree Procedures</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in three
formats: this web page (for browsing content), PDF (comparable to original document formatting), and 
 WordPerfect. To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 








THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURTFOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA






UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,    
         
       
Plaintiff,

            
                v. 

ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and    		
BOWATER INCORPORATED,
         
       
 Defendants.




    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


CASE NO:
JUDGE:                   		
DECK TYPE: Antitrust
DATE STAMPED:
    


PLAINTIFF UNITED STATES' EXPLANATION OFCONSENT DECREE PROCEDURES
Plaintiff United States of America submits this memorandum summarizing the
procedures for entry of the proposed Final Judgment as set forth by the Antitrust Procedures and
Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. §§ 16(b)-(h) (the "APPA"), which applies in civil antitrust cases
brought and settled by the United States.  As described below, the APPA provides that certain
events must occur prior to the Court signing and entering the proposed Final Judgment to resolve
this case. 

	1.  	Today, Plaintiff has filed a Complaint, proposed Final Judgment, Competitive
Impact Statement, and Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order (the "Stipulation"). 

	2.	Defendants have agreed in the Stipulation that they will abide by the terms of the
proposed Final Judgment in the interim and also follow certain procedures described in the
Stipulation between consummation of their merger and the divestitures required by the proposed
Final Judgment.  At this time, we ask that the Court only sign the Stipulation.

	3.     	The Stipulation also contains the parties' agreement that, after compliance with
the APPA, the Court may enter the proposed Final Judgment.  The APPA requires that Plaintiff
publish the proposed Final Judgment and the Competitive Impact Statement in the Federal
Register and in certain newspapers at least sixty (60) days prior to entry of the proposed Final
Judgment. The notice will inform members of the public that they may submit comments about
the proposed Final Judgment to the United States Department of Justice, Antitrust Division (see
15 U.S.C. §§ 16(b)-(c)). 

	4. 	During the sixty-day period, Plaintiff will consider, and at the close of that period
respond to, any comments that it has received, and it will publish the comments and Plaintiff's
responses in the Federal Register. 

	5. 	After the expiration of the sixty-day period, Plaintiff will file with the Court the
comments and Plaintiff's responses, and Plaintiff either will ask the Court to enter the Final
Judgment (subject to any proposed revisions) or will withdraw its consent to entry of the Final
Judgment, as provided in Section IV(A) of the Stipulation (see 15 U.S.C. § 16(d)). 

	6. 	If Plaintiff requests that the Court enter the proposed Final Judgment after
compliance with the APPA, 15 U.S.C. §§ 16(e)-(f), then the Court may enter the Final Judgment
without a hearing, provided that the Court concludes that the Final Judgment is in the public
interest.

Dated:	October 23, 2007


 


 
 
FOR PLAINTIFF
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA

   _______________/s/________________Karl D. Knutsen, Esq.

						Litigation I Section

						United States Department of Justice 

						Antitrust Division 

						1401 H Street NW, Suite 4000

						Washington, DC 20530

						(202) 514-0976






 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    