
    <document>
        <title>Revised Final Judgment</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Aetna and The Prudential Insurance 
            Company</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in two
formats: this web page (for browsing content) and PDF (comparable to original document formatting). To view the PDF you will need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the
Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 







UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
          FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF TEXAS
          (DALLAS DIVISION)









            UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, and the
            STATE OF TEXAS
                              
             Plaintiffs,  

                              
            v. 

            AETNA INC., and
            THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE COMPANY  
            OF AMERICA,
                           
             Defendants.  



 |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |
            |          


Civil Action No 3-99CV 1398-H 
             Filed: 12/7/99 
          




REVISED FINAL JUDGMENT
WHEREAS, plaintiffs, the United States of America and the State of Texas, 
        filed a Complaint in this action on June 21, 1999, and plaintiffs and 
        defendants, by their respective attorneys, having consented to the entry 
        of this Revised Final Judgment without trial or adjudication of any issue 
        of fact or law herein, and without this Revised Final Judgment constituting 
        any evidence against or an admission by any party with respect to any 
        issue of law or fact herein; 
      AND WHEREAS, defendants have agreed to be bound by the provisions of 
        this Revised Final Judgment pending its approval by the Court; 
      AND WHEREAS, plaintiffs intend to preserve competition by requiring Aetna 
        to divest its interests in the Houston operations of NYLCare Health Plans 
        of the Gulf Coast, Inc. and the Dallas operations of NYLCare Health Plans 
        of the Southwest, Inc., consisting of, among other assets, approximately 
        two hundred sixty thousand (260,000) and one hundred sixty seven thousand 
        (167,000) commercially insured HMO and HMO-based POS enrollees, respectively; 
      AND WHEREAS, plaintiffs require defendants to make the divestitures for 
        the purpose of establishing a viable competitor in the development, marketing, 
        and sale of HMO and HMO-based POS health plans in the Houston and Dallas 
        areas; 
      AND WHEREAS, plaintiffs require defendants to make the divestitures for 
        the purpose of redressing the effects that the United States and the State 
        of Texas allege would otherwise result from Aetna's proposed acquisition 
        of Prudential's health care assets, including the ability to depress physicians' 
        reimbursement rates in Houston and Dallas, which is likely to lead to 
        a reduction in quantity or a degradation in the quality of physician services 
        provided to patients in those areas; 
      AND WHEREAS, defendants have represented to plaintiffs that the divestitures 
        ordered herein can and will be made and that defendants will later raise 
        no claims of hardship or difficulty as grounds for asking the Court to 
        modify any of the divestiture provisions contained below; 
      NOW, THEREFORE, before the taking of any testimony, and without trial 
        or adjudication of any issue of fact or law herein, and upon consent of 
        the parties hereto, it is hereby ORDERED, ADJUDGED, AND DECREED as follows: 
      I. JURISDICTION
This Court has jurisdiction over each of the parties hereto and over 
        the subject matter of this action. The Complaint states a claim upon which 
        relief may be granted against defendants, as hereinafter defined, under 
        Section 7 of the Clayton Act, as amended (15 U.S.C. § 18). 
      

II. DEFINITIONS

As used in this Revised Final Judgment: 
      

 "Aetna" means Aetna Inc., a Connecticut corporation with its headquarters 
          and principal place of business in Hartford, Connecticut, its successors, 
          assigns, subsidiaries, divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships and 
          joint ventures, and its directors, officers, managers, agents, and employees. 
          
 "Dallas" means the entire service area of NYLCare-Southwest including, 
          but not limited to, the following Texas counties: Collin, Dallas, Denton, 
          Ellis, Grayson, Henderson, Hood, Hunt, Johnson, Kaufman, Parker, Rockwall, 
          and Tarrant. 
          
 "Excluded Assets" means those businesses of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and 
          NYLCare-Southwest that need not be divested, which consist of (1) all 
          Medicare HMO plans; (2) commercial HMO and HMO-based POS accounts not 
          located in Houston or Dallas; (3) provider network rental arrangements 
          for PPO plans; and (4) administrative services contracts with self-funded 
          plans. 
          
 "Houston" means the following Texas counties: Brazoria, Chambers, 
          Fort Bend, Galveston, Harris, Liberty, Montgomery, and Waller. 
          
 "NYLCare-Gulf Coast" means NYLCare Health Plans of the Gulf Coast, 
          Inc., a wholly owned subsidiary of Aetna that operates a licensed HMO 
          and HMO-based POS business under that name in Central and Southeastern 
          Texas, excepting the Excluded Assets, and includes: 
          

 all tangible assets necessary to compete in the sale or administration 
              of HMO and HMO-based POS plans; all personal property, inventory, 
              office furniture, fixed assets and fixtures, materials, supplies, 
              facilities, and other tangible property or improvements used in 
              the sale or administration of HMO and HMO-based POS plans; all licenses, 
              permits, and authorizations issued by any governmental organization 
              relating to HMO and HMO-based POS plans; contracts or agreements 
              for coverage of approximately two hundred sixty thousand (260,000) 
              commercially insured HMO and HMO-based POS plan enrollees; all other 
              contracts, agreements, leases, commitments, and understandings pertaining 
              to HMO and HMO-based POS plans; all contracts with accounts located 
              in Houston; all customer lists and credit records; and all other 
              records maintained in connection with the sale and administration 
              of HMO and HMO-based POS plans in Houston or Dallas; 
              
 all intangible assets relating to the sale or administration 
              of HMO and HMO-based POS plans, including but not limited to any 
              licenses and sublicenses, intellectual property, technical information, 
              know-how, trade secrets, programs, and all manuals and technical 
              information provided to employees, customers, suppliers, agents, 
              or licensees. 
          

 "NYLCare-Southwest" means NYLCare Health Plans of the Southwest, 
          Inc., a wholly owned subsidiary of Aetna that operates a licensed HMO 
          and HMO-based POS business under that name in Dallas, Fort Worth, and 
          several smaller cities in North Texas, including Paris, Tyler, Longview 
          and Amarillo, excepting the Excluded Assets, and includes: 
          

 all tangible assets necessary to compete in the sale or administration 
              of HMO and HMO-based POS plans; all personal property, inventory, 
              office furniture, fixed assets and fixtures, materials, supplies, 
              facilities, and other tangible property or improvements used in 
              the sale or administration of HMO and HMO-based POS plans; all licenses, 
              permits, and authorizations issued by any governmental organization 
              relating to HMO and HMO-based POS plans; contracts or agreements 
              for coverage of approximately one hundred sixty seven thousand (167,000) 
              commercially insured HMO and HMO-based POS plan enrollees; all other 
              contracts, agreements, leases, commitments, and understandings pertaining 
              to HMO and HMO-based POS plans; all contracts with accounts located 
              in Dallas; all customer lists and credit records; and all other 
              records maintained in connection with the sale and administration 
              of HMO and HMO-based POS plans in Dallas or Houston; 
              
 all intangible assets relating to the sale or administration 
              of HMO and HMO-based POS plans, including but not limited to any 
              licenses and sublicenses, intellectual property, technical information, 
              know-how, trade secrets, programs, and all manuals and technical 
              information provided to employees, customers, suppliers, agents, 
              or licensees. 
          

 "Prudential" means The Prudential Insurance Company of America, a 
          New Jersey mutual insurance company with its principal place of business 
          in Newark, New Jersey, its successors, assigns, subsidiaries, divisions, 
          groups, affiliates, partnerships and joint ventures, and directors, 
          officers, managers, agents, and employees. 
      
III. APPLICABILITY


 The provisions of this Revised Final Judgment apply to Aetna and 
          Prudential and to all other persons in active concert or participation 
          with any of them who shall have received actual notice of this Revised 
          Final Judgment by personal service or otherwise. 
          
 Aetna shall require, as a condition of the sale or other disposition 
          of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, that the acquirer agree 
          to be bound by the provisions of this Revised Final Judgment. 
      


IV. DIVESTITURE



 Aetna is hereby ordered and directed in accordance with the terms 
          of this Revised Final Judgment to divest its interests in NYLCare-Gulf 
          Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, excepting only the Excluded Assets, to 
          an acquirer(s) acceptable to the plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, 
          subject to Section XII. 
          
 Aetna is obligated to cause NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest 
          to maintain contracts or agreements for coverage of approximately two 
          hundred sixty thousand (260,000) commercially insured HMO and HMO-based 
          POS plan enrollees in Houston and contracts or agreements for coverage 
          of approximately one hundred sixty seven thousand (167,000) commercially 
          insured HMO and HMO-based POS plan enrollees in Dallas through the date 
          of signing the definitive purchase and sale agreement(s) for the divestiture 
          of the two NYLCare entities. Aetna may include related PPO business 
          as a part of the sale of the NYLCare entities, and the actual number 
          of such PPO enrollees as of the date of signing of the definitive purchase 
          and sale agreement(s) for the divestiture of the NYLCare entities will 
          be taken into account in determining Aetna's compliance with the membership 
          targets described herein. 
          
 Aetna shall use its best efforts to accomplish the divestitures as 
          expeditiously as possible and will accelerate the timetable for executing 
          the definitive purchase and sale agreement(s) for the divestiture of 
          the NYLCare entities to a target date of October 1, 1999. In any event, 
          Aetna shall execute definitive purchase and sale agreement(s) and shall 
          file all required applications for regulatory approval within one-hundred 
          and twenty (120) calendar days after June 21, 1999. Aetna shall complete 
          the divestitures within five (5) business days after it receives all 
          necessary regulatory approvals for divestiture of NYLCare-Gulf Coast 
          and NYLCare-Southwest and the acquisition of Prudential, or five (5) 
          business days after notice of the entry of this Revised Final Judgment 
          by the Court, whichever is later. 
          
 The plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, subject to Section XII, 
          may extend the time period for any divestitures for an additional period 
          of time not to exceed sixty (60) calendar days. If a further extension 
          is required to obtain necessary regulatory approvals, the plaintiffs, 
          in their sole discretion, subject to Section XII, may grant the time 
          necessary to obtain such approvals. 
          
 In accomplishing the divestitures ordered by this Revised Final Judgment, 
          Aetna promptly shall make known, by usual and customary means, the availability 
          for purchase of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. Aetna shall 
          inform any person making an inquiry regarding a possible purchase that 
          the sale is being made pursuant to this Revised Final Judgment and shall 
          provide such person with a copy of this Revised Final Judgment. Aetna 
          shall also offer to furnish to all prospective purchasers, subject to 
          reasonable confidentiality assurances, all information regarding NYLCare-Gulf 
          Coast and NYLCare-Southwest customarily provided in a due diligence 
          process, except information subject to the attorney-client privilege 
          or the attorney work-product privilege. Aetna shall make available such 
          non-privileged information to the United States and the State of Texas 
          at the same time that such information is made available to prospective 
          purchasers. 
          
 Aetna shall permit prospective purchasers to have reasonable access 
          to all NYLCare-Gulf Coast's and NYLCare-Southwest's personnel, physical 
          facilities, and any and all financial, operational or other documents 
          and information customarily provided as part of a due diligence process. 
          
 Aetna shall not take any action that will impede in any way the operation 
          of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest; shall immediately cease 
          all actions directed at the integration of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest 
          into Aetna. 
          
 Aetna shall take all steps necessary to ensure that NYLCare-Gulf 
          Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are maintained and operated as independent, 
          on-going, economically viable, and active competitors until completion 
          of the divestitures ordered by this Revised Final Judgment, including 
          but not limited to the following: 
          

 Aetna will appoint experienced senior management to run the combined 
              business of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. These executives 
              may be recruited from within the existing Aetna or NYLCare organizations, 
              with plaintiffs' approval, subject to Section XII, or from outside 
              the company. 
              
 Aetna will create a separate and independent sales organization 
              for NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
              
 Aetna will create a separate and independent provider relations 
              organization for NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
              
 Aetna will create a separate and independent patient management/quality 
              management organization for NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
              
 Aetna will create a separate and independent commercial operations 
              organization for the combined NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
              
 Aetna will create a separate and independent network operations 
              organization for the combined NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
              
 Aetna will create a separate and independent underwriting organization 
              for the combined NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
              
 Pursuant to transition services agreements approved by plaintiffs, 
              subject to Section XII, Aetna will provide certain support services 
              to NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. These services may 
              include human resources, legal, finance, actuarial, software and 
              computer operations support, and other services which are now provided 
              to NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest by other Aetna companies. 
              These transition services agreements will contain appropriate confidentiality 
              provisions to ensure that Aetna employees (other than the employees 
              performing services under the agreements) do not receive information 
              that Aetna is prohibited from receiving under Section III.E of the 
              Revised Hold Separate Stipulation and Order entered earlier. 
              
 Aetna will provide any additional transitional services requested 
              by the management of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and/or NYLCare-Southwest 
              in order to maintain the membership targets described in Section 
              IV.B. Such additional services may include, but not be limited to, 
              funding of service quality guarantees, subject to the approval of 
              the plaintiffs in their sole discretion, pursuant to Section XII. 
              
 Aetna will fund an incentive pool of at least $500,000, which 
              will be available to management of the NYLCare entities if they 
              meet the membership targets described in Section IV.B as of the 
              closing date for the sale of the NYLCare entities. 
          

 Aetna shall not take any action to consummate the proposed acquisition 
          of Prudential's health care business pursuant to the Asset Transfer 
          and Acquisition Agreement, dated as of December 9, 1998, or any subsequent 
          agreement between Aetna and Prudential, until such time as plaintiffs, 
          to their sole satisfaction, subject to Section XII, have determined 
          that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are independent, viable 
          competitors, that Aetna has complied with the terms of the Revised Hold 
          Separate Stipulation and Order entered previously, or until the divestitures 
          required by this Revised Final Judgment are complete. 
          
 Aetna shall request that the NYLCare entities provide the plaintiffs 
          with bi-weekly reports on total membership of the entities until the 
          divestitures required by this Revised Final Judgment are complete. 
          
 Unless the plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, subject to Section 
          XII, consent in writing, the divestitures pursuant to Section IV (or 
          by trustee appointed pursuant to Section V) shall include the entire 
          NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest businesses, excepting only 
          the Excluded Assets, operated pursuant to the Revised Hold Separate 
          Stipulation and Order entered previously in this proceeding, and shall 
          be accomplished by selling or otherwise conveying NYLCare-Gulf Coast 
          and NYLCare-Southwest to a purchaser(s) in such a way as to satisfy 
          the plaintiffs in their sole discretion, subject to Section XII, that 
          NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest can and will be used by the 
          purchaser(s) as part of a viable, ongoing business engaged in the sale 
          of HMO and HMO-based POS plans. These divestitures may be made to one 
          or more purchasers provided that in each instance it is demonstrated 
          to the sole satisfaction of the plaintiffs, subject to Section XII, 
          that the acquirer(s) will remain viable competitors. The divestitures, 
          whether pursuant to Section IV or Section V, shall be made to a purchaser(s) 
          for whom it is demonstrated to the plaintiffs' sole satisfaction, subject 
          to Section XII: (1) has the capability and intent of competing effectively 
          in the sale of HMO and HMO-based POS plans in Dallas and Houston; (2) 
          has the managerial, operational, and financial capability to compete 
          effectively in the sale of HMO and HMO-based POS plans in Houston and 
          Dallas; and (3) is not restrained through any agreement with Aetna or 
          otherwise in its ability to compete effectively in the sale of HMO and 
          HMO-based POS plans in Dallas and Houston. 
          
 For a period of one year from the date of the completion of the divestiture, 
          Aetna shall not hire or solicit to hire any individual who, on the date 
          of the divestiture, was an employee of NYLCare-Gulf Coast or NYLCare-Southwest, 
          unless such individual has (1) a written offer of employment from a 
          third party for a like position, or (2) a written notice from the acquirer 
          of NYLCare-Gulf Coast or NYLCare-Southwest, stating that the company 
          does not intend to continue to employ the individual in a like position. 
      


V. APPOINTMENT OF TRUSTEE



 In the event that Aetna has not divested NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest 
          within the time specified in Section IV, the Court shall appoint, on 
          application of the plaintiffs, a trustee selected by the plaintiffs 
          in their sole discretion, subject to Section XII, to effect the required 
          divestitures. 
          
 After the appointment of a trustee becomes effective, only the trustee 
          shall have the right to sell NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, 
          as described in Sections II.E and II.F. The trustee shall have the power 
          and authority to accomplish the divestitures at the best price then 
          obtainable upon a reasonable effort by the trustee, subject to the provisions 
          of Sections IV and VI, and shall have such other powers as the Court 
          shall deem appropriate. Subject to Section V.C, the trustee shall have 
          the power and authority to hire, at the cost and expense of Aetna, any 
          investment bankers, attorneys, or other agents reasonably necessary 
          in the judgment of the trustee to assist in the divestitures, and such 
          professionals and agents shall be accountable solely to the trustee. 
          The trustee shall have the power and authority to accomplish the divestitures 
          at the earliest possible time to a purchaser acceptable to the plaintiffs 
          in their sole discretion, subject to Section XII; shall have the power 
          and authority to require Aetna to sell NYLCare's PPO business in Houston 
          and Dallas if the plaintiffs, in the exercise of their sole discretion, 
          subject to Section XII, determine that such a sale is necessary for 
          the preservation of competition; and shall have such other power and 
          authority as this Court shall deem appropriate. Aetna shall not object 
          to a sale by the trustee on any grounds other than the trustee's malfeasance. 
          Any such objections by Aetna must be conveyed in writing to the plaintiffs 
          and the trustee within ten (10) calendar days after the trustee has 
          provided the notice required under Section VI. 
          
 The trustee shall serve at the cost and expense of Aetna, on such 
          terms and conditions as the Court may prescribe, and shall account for 
          all monies derived from the sale of the assets sold by the trustee and 
          all costs and expenses so incurred. After approval by the Court of the 
          trustee's accounting, including fees for its services and those of any 
          professionals and agents retained by the trustee, all remaining money 
          shall be paid to Aetna and the trust shall then be terminated. The compensation 
          of such trustee and of any professionals and agents retained by the 
          trustee shall be reasonable in light of the value of the divested business 
          and based on a fee arrangement providing the trustee with an incentive 
          based on the price and terms of the divestitures and the speed with 
          which they are accomplished. 
          
 Aetna shall use its best efforts to assist the trustee in accomplishing 
          the required divestitures, including best efforts to effect all necessary 
          regulatory approvals. The trustee and any consultants, accountants, 
          attorneys, and other persons retained by the trustee shall have full 
          and complete access to the personnel, books, records, and facilities 
          of the businesses to be divested, and Aetna shall develop financial 
          or other information relevant to the business to be divested customarily 
          provided in a due diligence process as the trustee may reasonably request, 
          subject to customary confidentiality assurances. Aetna shall permit 
          prospective purchasers of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest to 
          have reasonable access to personnel and to make such inspection of physical 
          facilities and any and all financial, operational or other documents 
          and other information as may be relevant to the divestitures required 
          by this Revised Final Judgment. 
          
 After its appointment, the trustee shall file monthly reports with 
          the parties and the Court setting forth the trustee's efforts to accomplish 
          the divestitures ordered under this Revised Final Judgment; provided, 
          however, that to the extent such reports contain information that the 
          trustee deems confidential, such reports may be filed under seal for 
          in camera review. Such reports shall include the name, address 
          and telephone number of each person who, during the preceding month, 
          made an offer to acquire, expressed an interest in acquiring, entered 
          into negotiations to acquire, or was contacted or made an inquiry about 
          acquiring, any interest in the business to be divested, and shall describe 
          in detail each contact with any such person during that period. The 
          trustee shall maintain full records of all efforts made to divest the 
          businesses to be divested. 
          
 If the trustee has not accomplished such divestitures within six 
          (6) months after its appointment, the trustee thereupon shall file promptly 
          with the Court a report setting forth (1) the trustee's efforts to accomplish 
          the required divestitures; (2) the reasons, in the trustee's judgment, 
          why the required divestitures have not been accomplished; and (3) the 
          trustee's recommendations; provided, however, that to the extent such 
          reports contain information that the trustee deems confidential, such 
          reports may be filed under seal for in camera review. The trustee 
          shall at the same time furnish such report to the parties, who shall 
          each have the right to be heard and to make additional recommendations 
          consistent with the purpose of the trust. The Court shall enter thereafter 
          such orders as it shall deem appropriate in order to carry out the purpose 
          of the trust which may, if necessary, include extending the trust and 
          the term of the trustee's appointment by a period requested by the plaintiffs, 
          subject to Section XII. 
      



VI. NOTIFICATION
Within two (2) business days following execution of a definitive agreement, 
        contingent upon compliance with the terms of this Revised Final Judgment, 
        to effect, in whole or in part, any proposed divestitures pursuant to 
        Section IV or Section V, Aetna or the trustee, whichever is then responsible 
        for effecting the divestitures, shall notify the United States and the 
        State of Texas of the proposed divestitures. If the trustee is responsible, 
        it shall similarly notify Aetna. The notice shall set forth the details 
        of the proposed transaction and list the name, address, and telephone 
        number of each person not previously identified who offered to, or expressed 
        an interest in or a desire to, acquire any ownership interest in the businesses 
        to be divested that is the subject of the binding contract, together with 
        full details of same. Within ten (10) calendar days of their receipt of 
        such notice, the United States or the State of Texas may request from 
        Aetna, the trustee, the proposed purchaser, or any other third party additional 
        information concerning the proposed divestitures and the proposed purchaser. 
        Aetna and the trustee shall furnish any additional information requested 
        from them within ten (10) calendar days of the receipt of the request, 
        unless the parties shall otherwise agree. Within thirty (30) calendar 
        days after receipt of the notice or within twenty (20) calendar days after 
        the plaintiffs have been provided the additional information requested 
        from Aetna, the trustee, the proposed purchaser, and any third party, 
        whichever is later, the plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, subject 
        to Section XII, shall provide written notice to Aetna and the trustee, 
        if there is one, stating whether it objects to the proposed divestitures. 
        If the plaintiffs provide written notice to Aetna and the trustee that 
        they do not object, then the divestitures may be consummated, subject 
        only to Aetna's limited right to object to the sale under Section V.B. 
        Absent written notice that the plaintiffs do not object to the proposed 
        purchaser or upon objection by the plaintiffs, such divestitures proposed 
        under Section IV or Section V may not be consummated. Upon objection by 
        Aetna under Section V.B, a divestiture proposed under Section V shall 
        not be consummated unless approved by the Court. 
      

VII. AFFIDAVITS



 Within twenty-five (25) calendar days of the June 21, 1999 filing 
          of the original Hold Separate Order and Stipulation in this matter and 
          every thirty (30) calendar days thereafter until the divestitures have 
          been completed, whether pursuant to Section IV or Section V, Aetna shall 
          deliver to the United States and the State of Texas an affidavit as 
          to the fact and manner of compliance with Section IV or Section V. Each 
          such affidavit shall include, inter alia, the name, address, 
          and telephone number of each person who, at any time after the period 
          covered by the last such report, made an offer to acquire, expressed 
          an interest in acquiring, entered into negotiations to acquire, or was 
          contacted or made an inquiry about acquiring any interest in the business 
          to be divested, and shall describe in detail each contact with any such 
          person during that period. Each such affidavit shall also include a 
          description of the efforts that Aetna has made to solicit a buyer for 
          NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest and to provide required information 
          to prospective purchasers including the limitations, if any, on such 
          information. 
          
 Within twenty-five (25) calendar days of the June 21, 1999 filing 
          of the original Hold Separate Order and Stipulation in this matter, 
          Aetna shall deliver to the United States and the State of Texas an affidavit 
          that describes in detail all actions Aetna has taken and all steps Aetna 
          has implemented on an on-going basis to preserve NYLCare-Gulf Coast 
          and NYLCare-Southwest pursuant to Section VIII and the Revised Hold 
          Separate Stipulation and Order previously entered by this Court. The 
          affidavit also shall describe, but not be limited to, Aetna's efforts 
          to maintain and operate NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest as 
          active competitors, and the plans and timetable for Aetna's integration 
          of Prudential's healthcare assets. Aetna shall deliver to the United 
          States and the State of Texas an affidavit describing any changes to 
          the efforts and actions outlined in Aetna's earlier affidavit(s) filed 
          pursuant to this Section VII.B within fifteen (15) calendar days after 
          such change is implemented. 
          
 Until one year after the divestitures required by this Revised Final 
          Judgment have been completed, Aetna shall preserve all records of all 
          efforts made to preserve the businesses to be divested and effect the 
          divestitures. 
      


VIII. HOLD SEPARATE ORDER 

Until the divestitures required by this Revised Final Judgment have been 
        accomplished, Aetna shall take all steps necessary to comply with Section 
        IV and the Revised Hold Separate Stipulation and Order entered by this 
        Court, to preserve the assets of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, 
        and to ensure that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest remain viable 
        competitors in the sale of HMO and HMO-based POS plans in Dallas and Houston. 
        Defendants shall take no action that would jeopardize the divestitures 
        of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest. 
      IX. FINANCING
Aetna is ordered and directed not to finance all or any part of any purchase 
        by an acquirer(s) made pursuant to Section IV or Section V. 
      

X. COMPLIANCE INSPECTION

For the purpose of determining or securing compliance with this Revised 
        Final Judgment or for determining whether this Revised Final Judgment 
        should be modified or terminated, and subject to any legally recognized 
        privilege, from time to time: 
      

 Duly authorized representatives of the United States Department of 
          Justice, upon written request of the Attorney General of the United 
          States or the Assistant Attorney General in charge of the Antitrust 
          Division, or the State of Texas, upon written request by the Texas Attorney 
          General, and on reasonable notice to Aetna made to its principal offices, 
          shall be permitted: 
          

 Access during Aetna's office hours to inspect and copy all books, 
              ledgers, accounts, correspondence, memoranda, and other records 
              and documents, including computerized records, in the possession 
              or under the control of Aetna, which may have counsel present, relating 
              to any matters contained in this Revised Final Judgment and the 
              Revised Hold Separate Stipulation and Order; 
              
 Subject to the reasonable convenience of Aetna and without restraint 
              or interference from it, to interview, either informally or on the 
              record, its officers, employees, and agents, who may have counsel 
              present, regarding any such matters. 
          

 Upon the written request of the Attorney General of the United States, 
          the Assistant Attorney General in charge of the Antitrust Division, 
          or the Attorney General of the State of Texas, made to Aetna's principal 
          offices, Aetna shall submit such written reports, under oath if requested, 
          with respect to any matter contained in this Revised Final Judgment 
          and the Revised Hold Separate Stipulation and Order entered earlier 
          by this Court. 
          
 No information or documents obtained by the means provided in Section 
          VII or Section X shall be divulged by any representative of the plaintiffs 
          to any person other than a duly authorized representative of the Executive 
          Branch of the United States or of the State of Texas, except in the 
          course of legal proceedings to which the United States or the State 
          of Texas is a party (including grand jury proceedings), or for the purpose 
          of securing compliance with this Revised Final Judgment, or as otherwise 
          required by law. 
          
 If at the time Aetna furnishes to the United States or the State 
          of Texas information or documents, Aetna represents and identifies in 
          writing the material in any such information or documents for which 
          a claim of protection may be asserted under Rule 26(c)(7) of the Federal 
          Rules of Civil Procedure, and Aetna marks each pertinent page of such 
          material, "Subject to claim of protection under Rule 26(c)(7) of the 
          Federal Rules of Civil Procedure," then the United States or the State 
          of Texas shall give ten (10) calendar days' notice to Aetna prior to 
          divulging such material in any legal proceeding (other than a grand 
          jury proceeding) to which Aetna is not a party. 
      


XI. RETENTION OF JURISDICTION

Jurisdiction is retained by this Court for the purpose of enabling any 
        of the parties to this Revised Final Judgment to apply to this Court at 
        any time for such further orders and directions as may be necessary or 
        appropriate for the construction or carrying out of this Revised Final 
        Judgment, for the modification of any of the provisions hereof, for the 
        enforcement of compliance herewith, and for the punishment of any violations 
        hereof. 
      XII. MISCELLANEOUS
In the event plaintiffs are unable to agree on a course of action regarding 
        Sections IV.A, IV.D, IV.H, IV.I, IV.K, V.A, V.B, V.F, and VI in seven 
        days, then the United States may, in its sole discretion, act alone (or 
        decline to act) with respect to the course of action. 
      XIII. TERMINATION
Unless this Court grants an extension, this Revised Final Judgment will 
        expire on the tenth anniversary of the date of its entry. 
      XIV. PUBLIC INTEREST
Entry of this Revised Final Judgment is in the public interest. 
      Dated december 7, 1999. 
      


 

 _______________/s/________________
            United States District Judge 





 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    