
    <document>
        <title>Hold Separate Stipulation and
Order</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Aetna and The Prudential Insurance 
            Company</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in two
formats: this web page (for browsing content) and PDF (comparable to original document formatting). To view the PDF you will need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the
Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 






                   UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
                FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF TEXAS
                        (DALLAS DIVISION)








UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, and the           				
STATE OF TEXAS,               
           
Plaintiffs,


            
                v.    

AETNA INC., and									
THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE COMPANY OF AMERICA,
            
                           
Defendants.




	    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


Civil Action No.: 3-99CV 1398-H

Filed: June 21, 1999
                 

    




      HOLD SEPARATE STIPULATION AND ORDER

     It is hereby stipulated by and between the undersigned parties, by their respective
attorneys, subject to approval and entry by the Court, that:



                      I.   DEFINITIONS

     As used in this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order:
      
     A.   "Aetna" means defendant Aetna Inc., a Connecticut corporation with its
headquarters and principal place of business in Hartford, Connecticut, its successors, assigns,
subsidiaries, divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships, and joint ventures, and its directors,
officers, managers, agents, and employees.
      
     B.   "NYLCare-Gulf Coast" means NYLCare Health Plans of the Gulf Coast, Inc., a
wholly-owned subsidiary of Aetna that operates a licensed HMO and HMO-based POS business
under that name in Houston, Brazoria, Galveston, Austin, San Antonio, and Corpus Christi,
Texas.
      
     C.   "NYLCare-Southwest" means NYLCare Health Plans of the Southwest, Inc., a
wholly-owned subsidiary of Aetna that operates a licensed HMO and HMO-based POS business
under that name in Dallas, Fort Worth, and several smaller cities in North Texas, including Paris,
Tyler, Longview, and Amarillo.
      
     D.   "Prudential" means defendant The Prudential Insurance Company of America, a
New Jersey mutual insurance company with its principal place of business in Newark, New
Jersey, its successors, assigns, subsidiaries, divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships, and joint
ventures, and its directors, officers, managers, agents, and employees.
      
    II.   OBJECTIVES

     A.   The proposed Final Judgment filed in this case is meant to ensure Aetna's prompt
divestiture of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest for the purpose of maintaining
viable competitors in the sale of HMO and HMO-based POS plans and the purchase of physician
services, and to remedy the effects that the United States and the State of Texas allege would
otherwise result from Aetna's proposed acquisition of Prudential's health care assets.
      
     B.   This Hold Separate Stipulation and Order is intended to ensure, prior to such
divestiture, that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, which are being divested, be
maintained as independent, economically viable, ongoing business concerns, and that
competition is maintained during the pendency of the divestiture.
      
  III.   HOLD SEPARATE PROVISIONS

     Until the divestiture required by the Final Judgment has been accomplished:
      
     A.   Aetna shall immediately begin to take all steps necessary to preserve, maintain,
and operate NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest as independent competitors with
management, sales, service, underwriting, administration, and operations held entirely separate,
distinct, and apart from those of Aetna.  Aetna shall not coordinate the pricing, marketing, or sale
of health care services from NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest with the pricing,
marketing, or sale of health care services by Aetna.  Within twenty-five (25) calendar days of the
filing of the Complaint in this matter, Aetna will comply and inform plaintiffs of the steps taken
to comply with this provision.
      
     B.   Aetna shall take all steps necessary to ensure that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and
NYLCare-Southwest are maintained and operated as independent, ongoing, economically viable,
and active competitors, including but not limited to the following:




     Aetna will appoint experienced senior management to run the combined business
          of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest until the divestiture required      by
          the Final Judgment has been accomplished.  These executives may be recruited
          from within the existing Aetna or NYLCare organizations, with plaintiffs'
          approval, subject to Section IV.C, or from outside the company.

   Aetna will create a separate and independent sales organization for NYLCare-
          Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.

    Aetna will create a separate and independent provider relations organization for
          NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.

    Aetna will create a separate and independent patient management/quality
          management organization for NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.

   Aetna will create a separate and independent commercial operations organization
          for the combined NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.
    Aetna will create a separate and independent network operations organization for
          the combined NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.

   Aetna will create a separate and independent underwriting organization for the
          combined NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.


  Pursuant to transition services agreements approved by plaintiffs, subject to
          Section IV.C, Aetna will provide certain support services to NYLCare-Gulf Coast
          and NYLCare-Southwest until the divestiture. These services may include human
          resources, legal, finance, actuarial, software and computer operations support, and
          other services which are now provided to NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-
          Southwest by other Aetna companies.  These transition services agreements will
          contain appropriate confidentiality provisions to ensure that Aetna employees
          (other than the employees performing services under the agreements) do not
          receive information that Aetna is prohibited from receiving under paragraph III.C
          of this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order.



     C.   Aetna shall take all steps necessary to ensure that the management of NYLCare-
Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest will not be influenced by Aetna except as necessary to meet
Aetna's obligations as described below, and that the books, records, competitively sensitive
sales, marketing and pricing information, and decision-making associated with NYLCare-Gulf
Coast and NYLCare-Southwest will be kept separate and apart from the operations of Aetna.
Aetna's influence over NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest shall be limited to that
necessary to carry out Aetna's obligations under this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order, the
Final Judgment, and any applicable regulatory requirements, including all reserve or capital
requirements.  Aetna may receive aggregate historical financial information (excluding rate or
pricing information) relating to NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest to the extent
necessary to allow Aetna to prepare financial reports, tax returns, personnel reports, regulatory
filings, and other necessary or legally required reports.

     D.   Aetna shall maintain at either current levels or at the highest levels approved
during the year prior to Aetna's acquisition of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest,
whichever are higher, promotional, advertising, sales, technical assistance, marketing, and
merchandising support for NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, but in any event at
levels sufficient to ensure that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are economically
viable businesses.

     E.   Aetna shall provide and maintain all required reserves and sufficient working
capital to maintain NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest as economically viable,
ongoing businesses.

     F.   Aetna shall provide and maintain sufficient lines and sources of credit to maintain
NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest as economically viable, ongoing businesses.

     G.   Aetna shall not take any action to consummate the proposed acquisition of
Prudential's health care business pursuant to the Asset Transfer and Acquisition Agreement,
dated as of December 9, 1998, or any subsequent agreement between Aetna and Prudential, until
such time as the plaintiffs in their sole discretion, subject to Section IV.C, have determined that
NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are independent, viable competitors and that
Aetna has complied with this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order, or until the divestitures
required by the Final Judgment are complete.

     H.   Aetna shall not, except in the ordinary course of business, or as otherwise
permitted under this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order, or as part of a divestiture approved by
the plaintiffs in their sole discretion, subject to Section IV.C, remove, sell, lease, assign, transfer,
pledge as collateral for loans, or otherwise dispose of, any asset, tangible or intangible, of
NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.

     I.   Aetna shall maintain, in accordance with sound accounting principles, separate,
true, accurate, and complete financial ledgers, books, and records that report, on a periodic basis,
such as the last business day of every month, consistent with past practices, the assets, liabilities,
expenses, revenues, income, profit, and loss of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.

     J.   Until such time as NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are divested,
except in the ordinary course of business or as is otherwise consistent with this Hold Separate
Stipulation and Order, Aetna shall not hire, transfer, terminate, or alter, to the detriment of any
employee, any current employment or salary agreement for any employee who on the date of the
signing of this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order is employed at NYLCare-Gulf Coast or
NYLCare-Southwest.

     K.   Aetna may retain an independent consultant (the "Consultant") to monitor the
operations of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest until the divestiture(s) required by
the Final Judgment has been accomplished.  The Consultant shall have no role in the
management of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest, but shall be given reasonable
access to files, data, reports, and other information regarding the operations of NYLCare-Gulf
Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.  The Consultant's sole responsibility will be to report at least
monthly to Aetna's Director of Internal Audit, stating the Consultant's opinion on the question
whether NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are being managed in accordance with
applicable law, consistent with prudent underwriting and other industry standards, and consistent
with the fiduciary duties of its management.  If the Consultant's opinion on this question is
anything other than an unqualified "yes," the Consultant shall submit a written report stating the
basis for its opinion to the Director of Internal Audit, with a copy to the plaintiffs.  The
Consultant shall not transmit to Aetna any information that Aetna is prohibited from receiving
under paragraph III.C of this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order.  After receiving the
Consultant's written report, and with the consent of the plaintiffs in their sole discretion, subject
to Section IV.C, Aetna may take appropriate corrective action.

   IV.  OTHER PROVISIONS

     A.   Aetna shall take no action that would interfere with the ability of any trustee
appointed pursuant to the Final Judgment to complete the divestitures pursuant to the Final
Judgment to a suitable purchaser.

     B.   Prudential shall take no action that would hinder or obstruct Aetna's ability or
efforts to comply with this Hold Separate Stipulation and Order.

     C.   In the event plaintiffs are unable to agree on a course of action regarding any item
within their discretion in seven days, then the United States may, in its sole discretion, act alone
(or decline to act) with respect to that course of action.

     D.   With the consent of the plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, subject to Section IV.C,
Aetna may exclude certain NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest assets from this Hold
Separate Stipulation and Order.

     E.   This Hold Separate Stipulation and Order shall remain in effect until the
divestitures required by the Final Judgment are complete, or until further Order of this Court.

Respectfully submitted,


 FOR PLAINTIFF
              UNITED STATES OF AMERICA             
                                

              _______________/s/________________
              PAUL J. O'DONNELL
              Massachusetts Bar #547125
              U.S. Department of Justice
              Antitrust Division
              Health Care Task Force 
              325 Seventh Street, N.W., Suite 400
              Washington, D.C. 20530 
              Tel: (202) 616-5933
              Facsimile: (202) 514-1517


              FOR PLAINTIFF 
              STATE OF TEXAS 

              _______________/s/________________
              MARK TOBEY 
              Assistant Attorney General
              Chief, Antitrust Section
              State Bar No. 20082960 
              Office of the Attorney General
              P. O. Box 12548 
              Austin, Texas 78711-2548
              Tel: (512) 463-2185
              Facsimile (512) 320-0975 

 FOR DEFENDANT
              AETNA INC.
 _______________/s/________________
                ROBERT E. BLOCH
                D.C. Bar #175927
                Mayer, Brown & Platt
                1909 K Street, N.W.
                Washington, D.C. 20006
                Tel: (202) 263-3203
                Facsimile: (202) 263-3300


                FOR DEFENDANT
                THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE
                COMPANY OF AMERICA

                _______________/s/________________
                MICHAEL L. WEINER
                Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher & Flom, LLP
                New York Bar #MW0294
                919 Third Avenue
                New York, NY 10022
                Tel: (212) 735-2632
                Facsimile: (212) 451-7446 
              






IT IS SO ORDERED.


 Dated ______________________ , 1999.

 ______________________________
              United States District Judge   





 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    