
    <document>
        <title>Reply of the United States in Support of Entry of the Proposed Final
Judgment</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in three
formats: this web page (for browsing content), PDF (comparable to original document formatting), and 
 WordPerfect. To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 








THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA






UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,    
         
       
Plaintiff,

            
                v. 

ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and     

BOWATER INC.,
         
       
 Defendants.




    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          



CASE NO:  1:07-cv-1912 (RMC)


JUDGE: Collyer, Rosemary M.

DECK TYPE: Antitrust 


DATE STAMP: August 8, 2008
    






REPLY OF THE UNITED STATES IN SUPPORT OF ENTRY OF THE PROPOSED
FINAL JUDGMENT
INTRODUCTION
	The United States and the Newspaper Association of America ("NAA") agree that the
issue before the Court is whether the relief that the United States has secured in the proposed
Final Judgment meets the Tunney Act's public interest standard.(1)  Under this standard,

balancing of competing social and political interests affected by a proposed
antitrust consent decree must be left, in the first instance, to the discretion of the
Attorney General.  The court's role in protecting the public interest is one of
insuring that the government has not breached its duty to the public in consenting
to the decree.
United States v. Bechtel Corp., 648 F.2d 660, 666 (9th Cir. 1981).  As the United States explains
below, the public interest standard is a reasonableness test that incorporates substantial deference
to the Attorney General. 

	The United States disagrees with NAA on whether the relief required by the proposed
Final Judgment is adequate to the preserve competition that would have been lost as a result of
the defendants' merger.  The decision to require that relief, the divestiture of the Snowflake mill
in Snowflake, Arizona, was the result of a comprehensive nine-month investigation and was
based on the same detailed economic modeling that the United States used in deciding to
challenge the parties' transaction by bringing this case in the first instance.  NAA's claim that the
Snowflake divestiture is inadequate is based on flawed economic arguments that the
AbitibiBowater, Inc. ("AbitibiBowater"), exercised market power post-merger by closing
capacity and increasing newsprint prices.  The United States attaches herewith the Declaration of
Dr. Nicholas Hill to explain how the United States crafted the proposed remedy and to
demonstrate why NAA is wrong.  In making a public interest determination, the Court need not
determine which economist is correct; it only needs to find that the United States has presented a
reasonable basis for the proposed settlement.

	This reply brief is organized as follows: after discussing the applicable law, the United
States explains why the Snowflake divestiture is an appropriate remedy.  The United States then
explains why the nominal price increases upon which NAA relies do not demonstrate that
AbitibiBowater has exercised market power and appear instead to be the result of non-merger
related economic trends — a conclusion reinforced by the fact that newsprint price trends are
consistent with price trends for similar high volume paper products not affected by the merger. 
In addition, the United States explains that NAA ignores a critical fact: the mills that
AbitibiBowater closed were losing money during the investigation and at the time that they were
closed, which is enough in itself to undermine NAA's economic conclusions.  Finally, the United
States explains that the evidentiary hearing requested by NAA is unprecedented and unnecessary.
ARGUMENT

 The Court Must Enter The Proposed Final Judgment If It Determines That The
    Proposed Final Judgment Meets The Public Interest Standard.
	The Tunney Act provides that before entering the parties' settlement as its judgment, the
Court must "determine that the entry of such judgment is in the public interest."  15 U.S.C.
§ 16(e)(1).  Although the Act provides a non-exclusive list of factors that the Court "shall
consider" in making its determination,(2) the Act offers no explicit directives regarding the
standard the Court is to apply in making its determination.  Indeed, the statute does not define the
key phrase "in the public interest."  United States v. SBC Communications, Inc., 489 F. Supp. 2d
1, 10 (D.D.C. 2007) ("SBC").   In the three decades since its enactment, the courts (in particular,
those of this circuit) have drawn on the Act's language, structure, context, and legislative history
to flesh out that standard and the nature of this Court's task.  As Judge Sullivan found in his
recent decision examining the effect of the 2004 amendments to the Act, the "body of law
interpreting the Tunney Act's vague language" continues to govern post-amendment Tunney Act
proceedings.  Id. at 11.

	The United States has alleged conduct violating the antitrust laws — the defendants'
planned merger — and the competitive harm that would result if the merger were permitted to go
forward as defendants contemplated.  The United States' settlement expresses its conclusion that
the proposed decree adequately remedies (or prevents) the harm alleged in the Complaint, and
that it would therefore be in the public interest for the Court to enter it.(3)  The sole question for the
Court is whether to reject that conclusion.

	A court does not properly reject a proposed consent decree on the ground that a better
decree can be imagined.  The test instead is whether "the remedies [are] so inconsonant with the
allegations charged as to fall outside of the 'reaches of the public interest.'"  Microsoft, 56 F.3d
at 1461; see SBC, 489 F. Supp. 2d at 16 (noting that there "is no indication . . . that Congress
intended to overrule [Microsoft's 'reaches of the public interest'] holding" by the 2004
Amendments).  Thus a court may not "engage in an unrestricted evaluation of what relief would
best serve the public interest."  United States v. BNS, Inc., 858 F.2d 456, 462 (9th Cir. 1988)
(citation omitted).  Instead, it must recognize that Congress intended that the applicable public
interest concept encompass "compromises made for non-substantive reasons inherent in the
process of settling cases through the consent decree procedure," H.R. Rep. No. 93-1463, at 12
(1974), reprinted in 1974 U.S.C.C.A.N. 6535, 6542.  Embodied in precedent, the broad "reaches
of the public interest" standard logically follows from the Tunney Act's basic concept of judicial
consideration of a settlement,(4) and rejects the view that a court may simply "interpose its own
views of the appropriate remedy over those the government seeks as part of its overall
settlement."  Id. at 1458.

	After a court addresses the specific factors listed in the Tunney Act, its public interest
determination properly focuses on whether the terms of the decree are ambiguous, whether the
court "can foresee difficulties in implementation," and whether the proposed decree, as opposed
to defendants' conduct or other causes, would "positively injure[]" third parties.  Microsoft, 56
F.3d at 1462.(5)  But the primary focus in almost every case is whether "the remedies provided in
the decree [are] adequate to the allegations in the complaint," id. at 1457, in light of the "reaches
of the public interest" standard.

	In these circumstances, where an expert executive branch agency conducts an extensive
investigation and concludes that the public interest is served by a particular settlement, a court
should exercise considerable caution before declining to enter the proposed judgment.  The
decision to settle properly lies within the agency's "rather broad discretion."  Microsoft, 56 F.3d at
1461.  The "balancing of competing social and political interests affected by a proposed antitrust
consent decree must be left . . . .  to the discretion of the Attorney General."  Bechtel, 648 F.2d at
666.

	Beyond deference to the Attorney General's implicit balancing of interests, the court
properly gives deference to the United States' judgments as to the efficacy of remedial provisions. 
While the degree of deference may vary with the extent of the court's familiarity with the market
and other factors, Microsoft, 56 F.3d at 1461, the Court of Appeals has made clear that even a
court with considerable relevant expertise should not lightly reject the United States' predictions. 
Id.(6)
	Accordingly, the question is not whether the United States' view of the efficacy of the
remedies provided in the proposed decree is correct, but rather whether the United States has
established an "ample foundation for [its] judgment call" and thus shown "its conclusion
reasonable."  Microsoft, 56 F.3d at 1461; see also SBC, 489 F. Supp. 2d at 21 ("Even accounting
for [shortcomings that could reduce the effectiveness of the proposed settlements], the United
States has presented a reasonable basis for concluding that the proposed settlements will replace
much of the competition lost to the mergers, if perhaps not all of it.  Therefore, the Court finds
that the proposed settlements are reasonably adequate, and thus within the reaches of the public
interest.").



The United States' Judgment Regarding the Scope of Relief Is Reasonable
	The relief required under the proposed Final Judgment — the divestiture of the Snowflake,
Arizona newsprint mill — remedies the harm to competition alleged in the Complaint and easily
satisfies the public interest standard.(7)  During the course of its comprehensive nine-month
investigation, the United States conducted extensive discovery pursuant to 15 U.S.C. §§ 1311-1314, employed significant resources to review and analyze this information, determined that the
proposed merger would result in a substantial lessening of competition in the North American
newsprint market, and reached the conclusion that the divestiture of the Snowflake mill would
restore the competition that the merger would have otherwise eliminated.(8)   As part of this
investigation, the United States obtained a substantial production of documents and information
from the merging parties and issued 37 Civil Investigative Demands to third parties.  In total, the
United States received and considered more than 150,000 pages of material.  The United States
also conducted more than 60 interviews with customers, competitors, and other individuals with
knowledge of the industry, including NAA.

	To analyze the likely competitive effects of the merger, the United States used standard
microeconomic theories to model competition in the newsprint industry — analyzing a
comprehensive data set of prices, sales, production volumes, individual mill costs, capacities and
forecasts of North American newsprint demand. (See Response to Public Comments, at 14-15. 
See also Competitive Impact Statement, at 7-9 ("CIS")).  To help the Court understand the United
States' analysis and why NAA's claims are not correct, the United States is submitting with this
Reply the Declaration of Dr. Nicholas Hill, a Research Economist with the Department of Justice,
which, inter alia, discusses the methodology the Department employed in reaching its conclusion.

	This economic model used by the United States predicted that given mill costs and falling
demand Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. ("Abitibi") and Bowater Inc. ("Bowater") would close
unprofitable capacity regardless of the merger.  (Hill Declaration, ¶ ¶ 9-11).   The model also
predicted, however, that the merger would likely cause the combined firm to close profitable
plants as well in order anticompetitively to increase the price of newsprint.  (Id.)   The merger
created this incentive by combining the newsprint production capacity of the two firms, thereby
increasing the volume of newsprint over which the combined firm would benefit from a price
increase. 

	The United States used this same economic model to identify a divestiture that would be
sufficient to remove the merged firm's incentive to close profitable capacity by reducing the
volume of production over which the merged firm would benefit from a price increase.  (Id. at
11).  When an expert agency uses standard economic models to predict anticompetitive effects
and then uses these standard models to fashion relief, there is certainly a reasonable basis for
determining that the settlement proposed by the United States is in the public interest.


Post-Merger Increases In Newsprint Prices Are More Consistent With Subsequent
    Non-Merger-Related Events Such As Input Cost Increases Than With Market Power
	NAA claims that post-merger increases in nominal newsprint prices prove that the merged
firm is exercising market power.  However, NAA's assertion that the merger caused newsprint
prices to increase is not persuasive when one looks at real newsprint prices (which account for
inflation).  Real newsprint prices are actually lower than the nominal prices that NAA reports and
recent fluctuations in input prices, currency exchange rates, and other factors played important
roles in the recent newsprint price increases that NAA has identified.  Without further analysis of
input costs, exchange rate fluctuations, and other factors that have also driven prices higher for a
variety of other paper grades, the general observation of NAA's expert, Mr. John H. Preston that
newsprint prices have increased fails to support his conclusion that AbitibiBowater is exercising
market power as a result of the merger.  (See Hill Declaration, ¶¶ 12, 22-23).



Real Newsprint Prices Have Trended Downward Over Time and Actually
        Have Declined Since The Merger Announcement
        

    


	Dr. Hill reviewed ten years of public newsprint sales data and adjusted the data for
inflation.  The real newsprint price data make it clear that the recent increase in newsprint prices is
neither dramatic nor unprecedented, and that the nominal price increases NAA relies upon are not
a result of an exercise of market power by the merged firm, but instead are entirely consistent with
the volatile history of newsprint prices.  (Hill Declaration, ¶ ¶ 12-15, 19).  Real newsprint prices
appear to be trending downward over time.  (Id. at ¶ 19).  In fact, the real price of newsprint is
lower today than when the merger was announced.  (Id. at ¶ 15).  By ignoring the larger context,
focusing on a short time period, and presenting only a limited amount of information to the Court,
NAA tells an incomplete and misleadingly simple story. 



Currency Exchange Rates Have Affected U.S. Newsprint Prices as
        Canadian Producers Have Less Incentive To Produce Newsprint
        

    


	NAA's expert, Mr. Preston, recognizes that a rising Canadian dollar relative to the
American dollar raises the cost of Canadian production.  (Preston Declaration, ¶ 53).  However,
Mr. Preston fails to adjust properly his analysis for currency changes over time and therefore does
not account for a significant non-merger effect on the newsprint industry and prices in that
industry.  (See Hill Declaration, ¶ ¶ 16-19).     

	The exchange rate and its effect on Canadian producers are important to American
newsprint consumers because more than half of the newsprint consumed in the United States is
produced in Canada and many of the marginal newsprint producers whose costs determine
industry pricing are located in Canada.  (Id. at ¶ 16).  In addition, Canadian producers have had
less incentive to continue producing newsprint as their costs of manufacturing have increased
while their real revenues have not kept pace with these costs.  (Id. at ¶ 17).  One reason the cost of
producing newsprint in Canada has increased is because the Canadian dollar has gained against
the American dollar.  (Id. at ¶ 16).  Meanwhile, the average real price that Canadian producers
receive for newsprint in Canadian dollars has fallen over time.  (Id. at ¶ 17).  These facts are also
consistent with Dr. Hill's observation that it is Canadian — rather than American — mills which
have reduced capacity as the Canadian dollar has gained value relative to the American dollar.  
(Id. at ¶ 27). 



Input Costs Have Increased and Price Trends of Other Grades of Paper Are
        Similar to Newsprint
        

    


	Dr. Hill posits that another way to determine whether AbitibiBowater has been exercising
market power or simply responding to rising input costs is to compare price trends for newsprint
with products that have similar input costs.  (Hill Declaration,  ¶ 22).  Since the merger was
announced, the costs of fiber and fuel — two of newsprint's and similar paper products' major
inputs — have increased significantly.  (Id. at ¶ 14, n.6).  Dr. Hill then demonstrates that the prices
of these other grades of paper also rose significantly.  (Id. at ¶ 23).  The fact that the prices of
newsprint and other grades of paper rose together suggests that factors other than the merger have
driven newsprint prices higher, and undermines NAA's assertion that market power explains the
nominal newsprint price increases that have been observed post-merger.



NAA's Market Power Argument Ignores Important Facts

The Merged Firm Has Closed Only Unprofitable Mills
        
  


	NAA adopts the Complaint's theory of harm that the combined firm would have the
incentive to close profitable mills earlier than it would absent the merger.  (NAA Memorandum,
at 5).  Relying on a dominant firm theory, NAA recognizes that a test for whether a firm is
dominant is the firm's ability to close profitable mills: 

In a competitive market, the owner of a mill will continue to produce as the mill
covers its operating costs and makes some contribution, however small, to fixed
costs.  Closing a mill that is still able to sell its output at a profit above its
operating costs is a luxury that only a firm with market power can afford . . . . 
(NAA Memorandum, at 9-10 (emphasis added)).  NAA then goes on to assert that AbitibiBowater
closed 610,000 metric tonnes of newsprint capacity in late 2007 "in an exercise of market power,"
which has caused newsprint prices to increase.  (Id. at 11.  See also id. at 7-10).  

	NAA's explanation of the exercise of market power by a dominant firm — in this instance
AbitibiBowater — through closing profitable mills fatally disregards the fact that all the evidence
available indicates that the mills that AbitibiBowater closed were actually unprofitable.  (Hill
Declaration, ¶ 25 (quoting AbitibiBowater Executive Chairman John Weaver as stating: "All of
the capacity closed was in a negative cash position.")).  The United States has confirmed the
unprofitability of the closed mills by reviewing the defendant's confidential profit and loss
statements at these mills.  The United States explained that "the three mills that AbitibiBowater
closed after the merger were unprofitable" in its Response to Public Comments, (Response to
Public Comments, at 9), a public document that was filed with this Court and which was served
on NAA.  Nevertheless, NAA has ignored this critical fact.  It has failed to respond to the United
States' assertion in this proceeding or to AbitibiBowater's similar statement to the financial
community, and it has not provided any evidence that the closed mills were profitable. 

	NAA's faulty factual assumption — that the mills closed were profitable — leaves it with no
evidence that AbitibiBowater exercised market power as a dominant firm.  The United States
agrees that closing profitable mills would be evidence that market power was exercised.  Here,
however, NAA's factual premise is simply not true. 



Other Newsprint Producers Are Closing Mills
        



	If AbitibiBowater were exercising market power in order to drive newsprint prices up,
other firms in the industry would have a strong incentive to keep their mills open and even
attempt to increase production in order to profit from those higher prices.  (Hill Declaration, ¶
26).  However, several other firms also closed capacity in 2007 and 2008.  (Id.).  That these
firms closed their mills is not consistent with NAA's claim that AbitibiBowater is a dominant
firm exercising market power.  (Id.).  Instead, these closures suggest that the combined firm's
decision to reduce unprofitable capacity was driven by factors other than the merger.  (Id.).



Granting NAA's Request For An Evidentiary Hearing Would Be Unprecedented
    And Such A Theory Is Unnecessary
	Despite proclaiming that the existing record is "more than adequate" to make a public
interest determination, (NAA Memorandum, at 14), NAA calls for an evidentiary hearing to
expand the record in this case "if this matter is to be decided based on a choice between
competing data sets and economic models."  (Id.).  That is not the legal standard, however.  
The Court is not faced with a choice between competing data sets and economic models, but
with the question of whether the proposed Final Judgment is in the public interest.  The record
is more than adequate for the Court to decide the question that is actually before it, and thus an
evidentiary hearing is both unnecessary and ill-advised.(9)
	Although the Tunney Act permits a court to conduct an evidentiary hearing when
necessary, 15 U.S.C. § 16(f), Congress contemplated that "the trial judge will adduce the
necessary information through the least complicated and least time-consuming means
possible."  S. Rep. No. 93-298, at 6 (1973) ("Senate Report"); accord H.R. Rep. No. 93-1463,
at 8 (1974), reprinted in 1974 U.S.C.C.A.N. 6535, 6539 ("House Report").  Ordinarily, this
principle rules out an evidentiary hearing.(10)  Indeed, the United States is unaware that an
evidentiary hearing has ever been held in a Tunney Act proceeding in any jurisdiction.(11)
	NAA's argument does not warrant departing from standard Tunney Act practice in this
case.  The Court must decide whether entry of the proposed decree would be within the
"reaches of the public interest," which in turn requires deciding not whether the United States'
conclusion expressed in the CIS and in Dr. Hill's Declaration is correct, but rather whether "the
government has presented a reasonable basis for concluding that the proposed settlements will
replace much of the competition lost to the merger[]."  SBC, 489 F. Supp. 2d at 21.  That
question is easily answered here on the basis of the existing record and it is unnecessary to take
the unprecedented step of holding an evidentiary hearing to determine whether entry of the
proposed Final Judgment is in the public interest.


CONCLUSION
	For the reasons set forth in this Memorandum, the Motion To Enter the Proposed Final
Judgment, the United States' Response to Public Comments, and the CIS, there is plainly a
reasonable basis for the United States' conclusion that the proposed Final Judgment is in the
public interest.  The United States therefore requests that the Court so find, deny NAA's
request for an evidentiary hearing, and enter the proposed Final Judgment. 





Dated: August 8, 2008
     
                              Respectfully submitted,






      
     
 

   _______________/s/________________
   Karl D. Knutsen

							Ryan Danks

							Rebecca Perlmutter

							Michelle Seltzer (D.C. Bar No. 475482)

							Trial Attorneys

							Litigation I Section

							Antitrust Division

							United States Department of Justice

							1401 H St., N.W., Suite 4000

							Washington, D.C. 20530

							Telephone: (202) 514-0976

							Facsimile:   (202) 307-5802
   
   
   







CERTIFICATE OF SERVICE PURSUANT TO LOCAL RULE 5.4</text>
    </document>
    