
    <document>
        <title>[Proposed] Final Judgment</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in three
formats: this web page (for browsing content), PDF (comparable to original document formatting), and 
 WordPerfect. To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 








THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURTFOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA 






UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,    
         
       
Plaintiff,

            
                v. 

ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and   
BOWATER INCORPORATED,
         
       
 Defendants.




    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


CASE NO.:


JUDGE:  


DECK TYPE: Antitrust 


DATE STAMP:
    


FINAL JUDGMENT
	WHEREAS, Plaintiff, United States of America, filed its Complaint on 
October 23, 2007, and Plaintiff and Defendants, Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. ("Abitibi") and
Bowater Incorporated ("Bowater"), by their respective attorneys, have consented to the entry of
this Final Judgment without trial or adjudication of any issue of fact or law, and without this
Final Judgment constituting any evidence against or admission by any party regarding any issue
of fact or law; 

	AND WHEREAS, Defendants agree to be bound by the provisions of this Final Judgment
pending its approval by the Court; 

	AND WHEREAS, the essence of this Final Judgment is the prompt and certain 
divestiture of certain rights or assets by Defendants to assure that competition is not substantially 
lessened;

	AND WHEREAS, the United States requires Defendants to make certain divestitures for 
the purpose of remedying the loss of competition alleged in the Complaint; 

	AND WHEREAS, Defendants have represented to the United States that the divestitures
required below can and will be made and that Defendants will later raise no claim of hardship or 
difficulty as grounds for asking the Court to modify any of the divestiture provisions contained 
below;

	NOW THEREFORE, before any testimony is taken, without trial or adjudication of any 
issue of  fact or law, and upon consent of the parties, it is ORDERED, ADJUDGED, AND 
DECREED:

I. Jurisdiction
This Court has jurisdiction over the subject matter of and each of the parties to this 
action.  The Complaint states a claim upon which relief may be granted against Defendants under
Section 7 of the Clayton Act, 15 U.S.C. § 18. 

II. Definitions
	As used in this Final Judgment:

	A.	"Acquirer" means the entity or entities to whom Defendants divest some or all of 
the Divestiture Assets.

	B.	"Abitibi" means Defendant Abitibi-Consolidated Inc., a Canadian corporation 
with its headquarters in Montréal, Quebec, Canada, its successors and assigns, and its 
subsidiaries, divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships and joint ventures, and their directors, 
officers, managers, agents, and employees. 

	C.	"Bowater" means Defendant Bowater Incorporated, a Delaware corporation with
its  headquarters in Greenville, South Carolina, its successors and assigns, and its subsidiaries, 
divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships and joint ventures, and their directors, officers, 
managers, agents, and employees. 

D.	"Newsprint" means the lowest grade of uncoated groundwood paper (i.e., paper
manufactured from mechanically processed pulp), regardless of its basis weight.  It is primarily
used in the production of newspapers, but also used in some advertising inserts, comic books,
trade publications, and direct mail, among other end-use products.

E.	 "Divestiture Assets" means: 

Abitibi's Snowflake, Arizona newsprint mill, located at Spur 277 North, 
Snowflake, Arizona 85937;

	all tangible assets used in the mill listed in Section II(E)(1), including all
assets relating to research and development activities, manufacturing
equipment, tooling and fixed assets, real property (leased or owned),
personal property, inventory, newsprint reserves, office furniture,
materials, supplies, docking facilities, on- or off-site warehouses or storage
facilities relating to the mill, Apache Railway Company assets; all
licenses, permits and authorizations issued by any governmental
organization relating to the mill; all contracts, agreements, leases
(including renewal rights), commitments, certifications, and
understandings relating to the mill, including supply agreements; all
customer lists, contracts, accounts, and credit records relating to the mill;
all interests in, and contracts relating to, power generation; all repair and
performance records and all other records relating to the mill; and               
                                                           

	all intangible assets used in the development, production, servicing, 
distribution, and sales of products manufactured by the mill listed in 

				Section II(E)(1), including but not limited to all contractual rights, patents,
						licenses and sublicenses, intellectual property, technical information, 

				computer software and related documentation, know-how, trade secrets, 

				drawings, blueprints, designs, design protocols, specifications for 

				materials, specifications for parts and devices, safety procedures for the 

				handling of materials and substances, quality assurance and control 

				procedures, design tools and simulation capability, all manuals and 

				technical information provided to the employees, customers, suppliers, 

				agents or licensees, and all research data concerning historic and current 

				research and development efforts relating to the mill, including, but not 

				limited to designs of experiments, and the results of successful and 

				unsuccessful designs and experiments.
III. Applicability
		A.	This Final Judgment applies to Defendants, as defined above, and all other 
persons in active concert or participation with Defendants who receive actual notice of this Final 
Judgment by personal service or otherwise. 

		B.	If, prior to complying with Section IV and V of this Final Judgment, Defendants 

sell or otherwise dispose of all or substantially all of their assets that include the Divestiture 

Assets, they shall require, as a condition of the sale or other disposition, that the purchaser 

agrees to be bound by the provisions of this Final Judgment.  Defendants need not obtain such an 

agreement from the Acquirer of the assets divested pursuant to this Final Judgment. 

IV. Divestitures
	A.	Defendants are ordered and directed, within 120 calendar days after the

filing of the Complaint in this matter, or five (5) days after notice of the entry of this Final 

Judgment by the Court, whichever is later, to divest the Divestiture Assets in a manner consistent 

with this Final Judgment to an Acquirer acceptable to the United States in its sole discretion. The 

United States, in its sole discretion, may agree to one or more extensions of this time period not 

to exceed sixty (60) days in total, and shall notify the Court in such circumstances.  Defendants 

agree to use their best efforts to divest the Divestiture Assets as expeditiously as possible. 

	B.	In accomplishing the divestitures ordered by the Final Judgment, Defendants 

promptly shall make known, by usual and customary means, the availability of the Divestiture 

Assets.  Defendants shall inform any person making inquiry regarding a possible purchase of the 

Divestiture Assets that they are being divested pursuant to this Final Judgment and provide that 

person with a copy of this Final Judgment.  Unless the United States otherwise consents in 

writing, Defendants shall offer to furnish to all prospective Acquirers, subject to customary 

confidentiality assurances, all information and documents relating to the Divestiture Assets that 

customarily are provided in a due diligence process except such information or documents 

subject to the attorney-client or work-product privilege.  Defendants shall make available such 

information to the United States at the same time that such information is made available to any 

other person. 

	C.	Unless the United States otherwise consents in writing, Defendants shall provide 

the Acquirer and the United States information relating to personnel involved in production, 

operations, and sales at the Divestiture Assets to enable the Acquirer to make offers of 

employment.  Defendants will not interfere with any negotiations by the Acquirer to employ any 

employee of the Divestiture Assets whose primary responsibility is production, operations, or 

sales at the Divestiture Assets. 

	D.	Unless the United States otherwise consents in writing, Defendants shall permit 

prospective Acquirers of the Divestiture Assets to have reasonable access to personnel and to 

make inspections of the physical facilities of the Divestiture Assets; access to any and all  

environmental, zoning, and other permit documents and information; and access to any and all 

financial, operational, and other documents and information customarily provided as part of a 

due diligence process. 

	E.	Defendants shall warrant to the Acquirer of the Divestiture Assets that each asset 

will be operational on the date of sale.

	F.	Defendants shall not take any action that will impede in any way the permitting, 

operation, or divestiture of the Divestiture Assets. 

G.	At the option of the Acquirer, Defendants shall enter into a fiber supply contract 

for old newsprint (ONP) sufficient to meet 25% of the Acquirer's needs for a period of up to 

three (3) years from the date of the divestiture. The terms and conditions of any such contract 

must be reasonably related to market conditions for old newsprint and the purchase price shall be
set at the prevailing market price. 

	H.	At the option of the purchaser and upon approval by the United States, in its sole
discretion, Defendants may enter into a transition services agreement based upon commercial
terms and conditions.  Such an agreement may not exceed twelve (12) months from the date of
the Divestiture.  Transition services may include information technology support, information
technology licensing, computer operations and data processing support, logistics support, and
such other services as are reasonably necessary to operate the Divestiture Assets. 

	I.	For the period from the date of the filing of the Complaint in this matter until one
(1) year after the sale of the Divestiture Assets, Defendants shall make available and deliver to
the Divestiture Assets within seven (7) business days the spare ceramic center roll from Abitibi's
Thorold, Ontario newsprint mill if: (a) the Acquirer or the person identified in Section V(K),
whomever is in control of the Divestiture Assets at the time, determines that the Divestiture
Assets' PM 3 machine requires a new ceramic center roll and (b) the Divestiture Assets'
permanent spare ceramic center roll, which has already been ordered, has not been delivered.  If
Defendants become obligated to deliver the spare ceramic center roll, then they may identify a
suitable alternative ceramic center roll and request permission from the United States, in its sole
discretion, to deliver the alternative center roll to the Divestiture Assets in place of the Thorold
center roll.  Such permission must be in writing.  In any event, Defendants must deliver the
Thorold center roll or an approved substitute to the Divestiture Assets within seven (7) business
days of being notified of the need for the Thorold roll.  Defendants will no longer be obligated to
provide a ceramic center roll to the Divestiture Assets if either of the ceramic center rolls in
Thorold's PM 6 or PM 7 machines break before the Divestiture Assets require a new ceramic
center roll.

	J.	Defendants shall warrant to the Acquirer that there are no material defects in the 

environmental, zoning, or other permits pertaining to the operation of the Divestiture Assets, and 

that following the sale of the Divestiture Assets, Defendants will not undertake, directly or 

indirectly, any challenges to the environmental, zoning, or other permits relating to the operation 

of the Divestiture Assets.

	K.	Unless the United States otherwise consents in writing, any divestiture pursuant to 

Section IV, or by trustee appointed pursuant to Section V, of this Final Judgment, shall include 

the entire Divestiture Assets, and shall be accomplished in such a way as to satisfy the United 

States, in its sole discretion, that the Divestiture Assets can and will be used by the Acquirer as a 

viable, ongoing business engaged in producing, distributing, and selling newsprint, that the 

Divestiture Assets will remain viable, and that the divestiture of such asset will remedy the 

competitive harm alleged in the Complaint.  The divestitures, whether pursuant to Section IV or 

Section V of this Final Judgment, 

 shall be made to an Acquirer that, in the United States' sole judgment, has 

					the intent and capability (including the necessary managerial, operational, 

					technical, and financial capability) to compete effectively in the 

					production, distribution, and sale of newsprint; and 

	shall be accomplished so as to satisfy the United States, in its sole 

				discretion, that none of the terms of any agreement between Acquirer and 						Defendants gives Defendants the ability to unreasonably raise the 

				Acquirer's costs, to lower the Acquirer's efficiency, or otherwise to 

				interfere in the ability of the Acquirer to compete effectively in the 

				production, distribution, and sale of newsprint.
V.  Appointment of Trustee to Effect Divestitures 
	A.	If Defendants have not divested the Divestiture Assets within the time period 

specified in Section IV(A), Defendants shall notify the United States of that fact in writing.  

Upon application of the United States, the Court shall appoint a trustee selected by the United 

States and approved by the Court to effect the divestiture of the Divestiture Assets. 

	B.	After the appointment of a trustee becomes effective, only the trustee shall have 

the right to sell the Divestiture Assets.  The trustee shall have the power and authority to 

accomplish the divestiture to an Acquirer acceptable to the United States at such price and on 

such terms as are then obtainable upon reasonable effort by the trustee, subject to the provisions 

of Sections IV, V, and VI of this Final Judgment, and shall have such other powers as this Court 

deems appropriate.  Subject to paragraph V(D) of this Final Judgment, the trustee may hire at the 

cost and expense of Defendants any investment bankers, attorneys, or other agents, who shall be 

solely accountable to the trustee, reasonably necessary in the trustee's judgment to assist in the 

divestiture. 

	C.	Defendants shall not object to a sale by the trustee on any ground other than the 

trustee's malfeasance.  Any such objection by Defendants must be conveyed in writing to the 

United States and the trustee within ten (10) calendar days after the trustee has provided the

notice required under Section VI. 

	D.	The trustee shall serve at the cost and expense of Defendants, on such terms 

and conditions as the United States approves, and shall account for all monies derived from the 

sale of the Divestiture Assets sold by the trustee and all costs and expenses so incurred.  After 

approval by the Court of the trustee's accounting, including fees for its services and those of any 

professionals and agents retained by the trustee, all remaining money shall be paid to 

Defendants and the trust shall then be terminated.  The compensation of the trustee and any 

professionals and agents retained by the trustee shall be reasonable in light of the value of the 

Divestiture Assets and based on a fee arrangement providing the trustee with an incentive based 

on the price and terms of the divestiture and the speed with which it is accomplished, but 

timeliness is paramount. 

	E.	Defendants shall use their best efforts to assist the trustee in accomplishing the 

required divestiture.  The trustee and any consultants, accountants, attorneys, and other persons 

retained by the trustee shall have full and complete access to the personnel, books, records, and 

facilities of the business to be divested, and Defendants shall develop financial and other 

information relevant to such business as the trustee may reasonably request, subject to reasonable
protection for trade secrets or other confidential research, development, or commercial
information.  Defendants shall take no action to interfere with or to impede the trustee's
accomplishment of the divestiture. 

	F.	After its appointment, the trustee shall file monthly reports with the United States 

and the Court setting forth the trustee's efforts to accomplish the divestiture ordered under this 

Final Judgment.  To the extent such reports contain information that the trustee deems 

confidential, such reports shall not be filed in the public docket of the Court.  Such reports shall 

include the name, address, and telephone number of each person who, during the preceding 

month, made an offer to acquire, expressed an interest in acquiring, entered into negotiations to 

acquire, or was contacted or made an inquiry about acquiring the Divestiture Assets, and shall 

describe in detail each contact with any such person.  The trustee shall maintain full records of all
efforts made to divest the Divestiture Assets. 

	G.	If the trustee has not accomplished such divestiture within six (6) months after its 

appointment, the trustee shall promptly file with the Court a report setting forth: (1) the trustee's 

efforts to accomplish the required divestiture; (2) the reasons, in the trustee's judgment, why the 

required divestiture has not been accomplished; and (3) the trustee's recommendations.  To the 

extent such report contains information that the trustee deems confidential, such report shall not 

be filed in the public docket of the Court.  The trustee shall at the same time furnish such report
to the United States, who shall have the right to make additional recommendations consistent
with the purpose of the trust.  The Court thereafter shall enter such orders as it shall deem
appropriate to carry out the purpose of the Final Judgment, which may, if necessary, include
extending the trust and the term of the trustee's appointment by a period requested by the United
States. 

VI.  Notice of Proposed Divestiture 
	A.	Within two (2) business days following execution of a definitive divestiture 

agreement, Defendants or the trustee, whichever is then responsible for effecting the divestiture 

required herein, shall notify the United States of any proposed divestiture required by Section IV 

or V of this Final Judgment.  If the trustee is responsible, it shall similarly notify Defendants. 
The notice shall set forth the details of the proposed divestiture and list the name, address, and 

telephone number of each person not previously identified who offered or expressed an interest 

in or desire to acquire any ownership interest in the Divestiture Assets, together with full details 

of the same. 

	B.	Within fifteen (15) calendar days of receipt by the United States of such notice, 

the United States may request from Defendants, the proposed Acquirer, any other third party, or 

the trustee, if applicable, additional information concerning the proposed divestiture, the 

proposed Acquirer, and any other potential Acquirer.  Defendants and the trustee shall furnish 

any additional information requested within fifteen (15) calendar days of the receipt of the 

request, unless the parties shall otherwise agree. 

	C.	Within thirty (30) calendar days after receipt of the notice, or within twenty (20)
calendar days after the United States has been provided the additional information requested 

from Defendants, the proposed Acquirer, any third party, or the trustee, whichever is later, the 

United States shall provide written notice to Defendants and the trustee, if there is one, stating 

whether or not it objects to the proposed divestiture.  If the United States provides written notice 

that it does not object, the divestiture may be consummated, subject only to Defendants' limited 

right to object to the sale under Section V(C) of this Final Judgment.  Absent written notice that 

the United States does not object to the proposed Acquirer or upon objection by the United 

States, a divestiture proposed under Section IV or Section V shall not be consummated.  Upon 

objection by Defendants under paragraph V(C), a divestiture proposed under Section V shall not 

be consummated unless approved by the Court. 

VII.  Asset Preservation
	Until the divestiture required by this Final Judgment has been accomplished, Defendants
shall take all steps necessary to comply with the Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order entered
by this Court.  Defendants shall take no action that would jeopardize the divestiture ordered by
this Court. 

VIII. Affidavits 
	A.	Within twenty (20) calendar days of the filing of the Complaint in this matter, and 

every thirty (30) calendar days thereafter until the divestitures have been completed under 

Section IV or V, Defendants shall deliver to the United States an affidavit as to the fact and 

manner of its compliance with Section IV or V of this Final Judgment.  Each such affidavit shall 

include the name, address, and telephone number of each person who, during the preceding thirty 

days, made an offer to acquire, expressed an interest in acquiring, entered into negotiations to 

acquire, or was contacted or made an inquiry about acquiring, any interest in the Divestiture 

Assets, and shall describe in detail each contact with any such person during that period.  Each 

such affidavit shall also include a description of the efforts Defendants have taken to solicit 

buyers for the Divestiture Assets, and to provide required information to any prospective 

Acquirer, including the limitations, if any, on such information.  Assuming the information set 

forth in the affidavit is true and complete, any objection by the United States to information 

provided by Defendants, including limitations on the information, shall be made within 

fourteen (14) calendar days of receipt of such affidavit. 

	B.	Within twenty (20) calendar days of the filing of the Complaint in this matter, 

Defendants shall deliver to the United States an affidavit that describes in reasonable detail all 

actions Defendants have taken and all steps they have implemented on an ongoing basis to 

comply with Section VII of this Final Judgment.  Defendants shall deliver to the United States 

an affidavit describing any changes to the efforts and actions outlined in Defendants' earlier 

affidavits filed pursuant to this section within fifteen (15) calendar days after the change is 

implemented.

	C.	Defendants shall keep all records of all efforts made to preserve and divest the 

Divestiture Assets until one year after such divestiture has been completed. 


IX. Compliance Inspection
	A.	For the purposes of determining or securing compliance with this Final Judgment, 

or of determining whether the Final Judgment should be modified or vacated, and subject to any 

legally recognized privilege, from time to time duly authorized representatives of the United 

States Department of Justice, including consultants and other persons retained by the United 

States, shall, upon written request of a duly authorized representative of the Assistant Attorney 

General in charge of the Antitrust Division, and on reasonable notice to Defendants, be 

permitted: 

access during Defendants' office hours to inspect and copy, or at the 

				United States's option, to require Defendants to provide electronic or hard 

				copies of, all books, ledgers, accounts, records, data, and documents in the 

				possession, custody, or control of Defendants, relating to any matters 

				contained in this Final Judgment; and 

	to interview, either informally or on the record, Defendants' officers,
employees, or agents, who may have their individual counsel present, 

			regarding such matters. The interviews shall be subject to the reasonable 

			convenience of the interviewee and without restraint or interference by 

			Defendants. 
	B.	Upon the written request of a duly authorized representative of the Assistant 

Attorney General in charge of the Antitrust Division, Defendants shall submit written reports or 

responses to written interrogatories, under oath if requested, relating to any of the matters 

contained in this Final Judgment as may be requested.

	C.	No information or documents obtained by the means provided in this section shall 

be divulged by the United States to any person other than an authorized representative of the 

executive branch of the United States, except in the course of legal proceedings to which the 

United States is a party (including grand jury proceedings), or for the purpose of securing 

compliance with this Final Judgment, or as otherwise required by law. 

	D.	If, at the time information or documents are furnished by Defendants to the United
States, Defendants represent and identify in writing the material in any such information or
documents to which a claim of protection may be asserted under Rule 26(c)(7) of the Federal
Rules of Civil Procedure, and Defendants mark each pertinent page of such material, "Subject to
claim of protection under Rule 26(c)(7) of the Federal Rules of Civil Procedure," then the United
States shall give Defendants ten (10) calendar days notice prior to divulging such material in 
any legal proceeding (other than a grand jury proceeding). 

X. Notification of Future Transactions
	A.	Unless such transaction is otherwise subject to the reporting and waiting period 

requirements of the Hart-Scott-Rodino Antitrust Improvements Act of 1976, as amended, 15 

U.S.C. § 18a (the "HSR Act"), Defendants shall not, without notifying the United States, 

directly or indirectly acquire any assets or any interest, including any financial, security, loan, 

equity, or management interest, in any of Defendants' jointly-owned newsprint mills or

 machines if the value of such acquisition exceeds $2,000,000.  Defendants are exempted from

this notice provision if either (1) from the date of the filing of the Complaint in this matter, the
acquisition accounts for less than a 5% change in any interest and does not change control in any
of Defendants' jointly-owned mills or machines, or (2) the acquisition is the direct result of an
asset swap between one of Defendants' jointly-owned mills or machines to another of
Defendants' mills or machines of the same character, and (3) such transaction is not otherwise
subject to the requirements of the HSR Act.  This notification requirement shall run for a period
of ten (10) years from the entry of this Final Judgment.

	Provided, however, that the following transactions shall be exempt from the notice
requirement: (1) Defendants further investing in a pre-existing jointly-owned mill or machine on
a pro-rata basis with Defendants' partner(s); and (2) loans (including guarantees and security
interests on loans) for the following purposes, provided that they do not enable any distribution
from the joint venture to Defendants or Defendants' joint venture partner(s) that would not have
otherwise occurred: (i) capital expenditures relating to pre-existing jointly-owned mills or
machines, (ii) working capital transactions of the same character that Defendants have engaged in
over the past ten (10) years; (iii) debt repayment or refinancing which does not impact equity
share or the relative effective return between Defendants and their partner(s); and (iv) mergers or
acquisitions other than those relating to newsprint mills or machines. 

	B.	Such notification shall be provided to the United States in the same format as, and
per the instructions relating to, the Notification and Report Form set forth in the Appendix to Part
803 of Title 16 of the Code of Federal Regulations as amended, except that the information
requested in Items 5 through 9 of the instructions must be provided only about newsprint, and the
required filing fee under the HSR Act shall be waived.  Notification shall be provided at least
thirty (30) days prior to acquiring any such assets or interest, and shall include, beyond what may
be required by the applicable instructions, the names of the principal representatives of the
parties to the agreement who negotiated the agreement, and any management or strategic plans
discussing the proposed transaction.  This Section shall be broadly construed and any ambiguity
or uncertainty regarding the filing of notice under this Section shall be resolved in favor of filing
notice.

XI. No Reacquisition
	Defendants may not reacquire any part of the Divestiture Assets during the term of this 
Final Judgment.

XII. Retention of Jurisdiction 
	This Court retains jurisdiction to enable any party to this Final Judgment to apply to this 
Court at any time for further orders and directions as may be necessary or appropriate to carry out
or construe this Final Judgment, to modify any of its provisions, to enforce compliance, and to
punish violations of its provisions. 

XIII. Expiration of Final Judgment 
	Unless this Court grants an extension, this Final Judgment shall expire ten (10) years 
from the date of its entry. 

XIV. Public Interest Determination
	Entry of this Final Judgment is in the public interest. The parties have complied with the 

requirements of the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. § 16, including making 

copies available to the public of this Final Judgment, the Competitive Impact Statement, and any 

comments thereon and the United States's responses to comments.  Based upon the record before 

the Court, which includes the Competitive Impact Statement and any comments and response to 

comments filed with the Court, entry of this Final Judgment is in the public interest. 

Date: ______________


 


 
 
Court approval subject to procedures of the
Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act, 
15 U.S.C. § 16. 

   _______________________________United States District Judge






 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    