
    <document>
        <title>Certificate of Compliance with
Provisions of the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in three
formats: this web page (for browsing content), PDF (comparable to original document formatting), and 
 WordPerfect. To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 









THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA 







UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,    
         
       
Plaintiff,

            
                v. 
              ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and   
                BOWATER INC.,
                                
                Defendants. 




    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
              |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          

 CASE NO: 1:07-cv-1912 
              JUDGE: Collyer, Rosemary M. 
              
DECK TYPE: Antitrust 
              DATE STAMP:
            



CERTIFICATE OF COMPLIANCE WITH PROVISIONS
OF THE ANTITRUST PROCEDURES AND PENALTIES ACT
	Plaintiff United States of America, by the undersigned attorneys, hereby certifies that, in
compliance with the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. § 16(b)-(h) ("APPA" or
"Tunney Act"), the following procedures have been followed in preparation for the entry of the
final judgment herein:

 1. Plaintiff and defendants stipulated to the entry of the proposed Final 
  Judgment on October 23, 2007, and that Stipulation along with the proposed Final 
  Judgment and Competitive Impact Statement were filed with the Court on October 
  23, 2007; 
	2.   The Stipulation, proposed Final Judgment, and Competitive Impact Statement were
published in the Federal Register on November 8, 2007, see 72 Fed. Reg. 63,187 ( November 8,
2007);

	3.   A summary of the terms of the proposed Final Judgment was published in the
Washington Post, a newspaper of general circulation in the District of Columbia, starting on
November 18, 2007, and continuing for seven consecutive days through November 24, 2007;

	4.   Copies of the Stipulation, proposed Final Judgment, and Competitive Impact
Statement were furnished to all persons requesting them and made available on the Antitrust
Division's internet site;

	5.   On October 26, 2007, defendants Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and Bowater Inc. filed
with the Court their joint disclosure statement concerning written or oral communications by or
on behalf of the defendant, or any other person, with any officer or employee of the United States
concerning the proposed Final Judgment, as required by 15 U.S.C. § 16(g);

	6.   The sixty-day periods for this matter prescribed by 15 U.S.C. §16(b) - (d) for the
receipt and consideration of written comments, and during which the proposed Final Judgment
could not be entered, ended on January 23, 2008;

 	7.   The United States received one public comment on the proposed Final Judgment on
January 2, 2008, from the Newspaper Association of America ("NAA"); and	

	8.  The United States responded to the NAA's Comment on April 18, 2008, filing its
Response and the NAA's Comment with this Court;


9. The parties in this action have now satisfied all the requirements of the 
  Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. § 16(b)-(h), as a condition 
  for entering the proposed Final Judgment, and it is now appropriate for the 
  Court to make the necessary public interest determinations required by 15 U.S.C. 
  § 16(e) and to enter the proposed Final Judgment. 

 

Dated: June 18, 2008
     
                              Respectfully submitted,





  
 ____/s/___Karl D. Knutsen___
              Karl D. Knutsen, Esq. (karl.knutsen@usdoj.gov) 
              Ryan Danks, Esq. 
              Rebecca A. Perlmutter, Esq. 
              Michelle Seltzer, Esq. (D.C. Bar No. 475482) 
              U.S. Department of Justice, Antitrust Division 
              1401 H St., N.W., Suite 4000 
              Washington, DC 20530 
              T: (202) 514-0976 
              F: (202) 307-5802 






 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    