
    <document>
        <title>Information</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. ABB Middle East & Africa Participations 
            AG</case_name>
        <text>


  

This document is available in two formats: this web page (for browsing content) and 
PDF (comparable to original
document formatting). To view the PDF you will need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group.  











IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
     FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF ALABAMA
     SOUTHERN DIVISION







UNITED STATES OF AMERICA             
            
           


            
                v.    

ABB MIDDLE EAST & AFRICA
 PARTICIPATIONS AG,
            
                           
   Defendant.




    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


Criminal No. CR-01-N-135-S

Filed: April 11, 2001

Violation: 15 U.S.C. § 1            
    



 INFORMATION
  The United States of America, acting through its attorneys, charges:

I
DESCRIPTION OF THE OFFENSE
  1.   ABB MIDDLE EAST & AFRICA PARTICIPATIONS AG ("ABB MEA")
is made a defendant on the charge stated below.

  2.   Beginning at least as early as June 1989 and continuing until at least
September 20, 1996, the defendant and co-conspirators entered into and
participated in a combination and conspiracy to suppress and eliminate competition
by rigging the bids on Contract 29, a wastewater construction contract funded by
the United States Agency for International Development ("USAID") and performed
in the Arab Republic of Egypt.  The combination and conspiracy engaged in by the
defendant and co-conspirators was in unreasonable restraint of interstate and
foreign trade and commerce in violation of Section 1 of the Sherman Act, 
15 U.S.C. § 1.

  3.   The charged combination and conspiracy consisted of a continuing
agreement, understanding, and concert of action among the defendant and
co-conspirators, the substantial terms of which were to rig the bids on Contract 29.  

  4.   For the purpose of forming and carrying out the charged combination
and conspiracy, the defendant and co-conspirators did those things that they
combined and conspired to do, including, among other things:


  participating in meetings and conversations to discuss rigging
the bids on Contract 29; 

  agreeing, during those meetings and conversations, to bid at
certain levels and otherwise to increase the price level of bids on
Contract 29; 

  agreeing, during those meetings and conversations, to suppress
or eliminate competition on Contract 29; 

  agreeing, during those meetings and conversations, that co-conspirators
would be compensated $3.4 million by the
defendant in exchange for their commitments to suppress or
eliminate competition on Contract 29; 

  issuing bid tenders on Contract 29 in accordance with the
agreement reached; and

  receiving payments on Contract 29 from USAID.

II
BACKGROUND

  5.   As a result of the Camp David Peace Accords in the late 1970s, the
United States and other Western countries committed to fund extensive
rehabilitation work on the water treatment and disposal facilities in the Arab
Republic of Egypt.  Pursuant to this commitment, USAID, acting on behalf of the
United States, funded nearly a billion dollars in work by U.S. construction
companies in the late 1980s and early 1990s.  

  6.     The USAID-funded contracts were designed to be awarded to
prequalified United States contractors on the basis of competitive sealed bids.

III
DEFENDANT AND CO-CONSPIRATORS
  7.   During the period covered by this Information, SAE Sadelmi USA,
Inc., was a corporation organized and existing under the laws of New York with its
principal place of business in North Brunswick, New Jersey.  During the relevant
period, Elettrofin Societa Anonima Finanziaria Holding ("Elettrofin"), with its
principal place of business at Lugano, Switzerland (and later Milan, Italy and
subsequently Zurich, Switzerland), was responsible for the direction of its affiliate,
SAE Sadelmi USA, Inc.  In February, 1995, Elettrofin was sold to a third party, and
prior to the sale, Elettrofin's ownership in other companies was transferred to a
successor corporation, which is now known as ABB MIDDLE EAST & AFRICA
PARTICIPATIONS AG.  SAE Sadelmi USA, Inc. and ABB MEA were, at all times
during the relevant period, ultimately one hundred percent subsidiaries of ABB
Asea Brown Boveri, Limited, headquartered in Zurich, Switzerland.  ABB MEA,
under its prior name, engaged in coordinating the bidding efforts of SAE Sadelmi
USA, Inc. with its competitors on Contract 29.  

  8.   Various corporations and individuals not made defendants herein
participated as co-conspirators in the offense charged and performed acts and made
statements in furtherance thereof.

  9.   Wherever in this Information reference is made to any act, deed, or
transaction of a corporation, the reference means that the corporation engaged in
the act, deed, or transaction by or through its officers, directors, employees, or
representatives while they were actively engaged in the management, direction,
control, or transaction of its business or affairs. 

IV
TRADE AND COMMERCE
  10.  During the period covered by this Information, conspirators purchased
substantial quantities of supplies, materials, and equipment in anticipation of
bidding on and performing Contract 29.  The supplies, materials, and equipment
were shipped from the United States to the Arab Republic of Egypt in a continuous
and uninterrupted flow of interstate and foreign trade and commerce.

  11.  During the period covered by this Information, the activities of the
defendant and co-conspirators that are the subject of this Information were
within
the flow of, and substantially affected, interstate and foreign trade and commerce. 

V
JURISDICTION AND VENUE
  12.  The combination and conspiracy charged in this Information was
carried out, in part, within the Northern District of Alabama.


  13.  The combination and conspiracy charged in this Information was
carried out, in part,  within the five years preceding the filing of this Information.

  ALL IN VIOLATION OF TITLE 15, UNITED STATES CODE, SECTION 1.

Dated: 


/S/_____________________                                                       
JOHN M. NANNES            
Acting Assistant Attorney General
/S/_____________________                                                       
JAMES M. GRIFFIN               
Deputy Assistant Attorney General
/S/_____________________                                                       
SCOTT D. HAMMOND               
Director of Criminal Enforcement     
                              
Antitrust Division                  
U.S. Department of Justice
/S/_____________________                                                       
G. DOUGLAS JONES 
United States Attorney for the
Northern District of Alabama

/S/_____________________                                                 
JOHN T. ORR
Chief, Atlanta Office
/S/_____________________                                                  
WILLIAM D. DILLON
JON R. SMIBERT

Attorneys, Antitrust Division
U.S. Department of Justice
Richard B. Russell Building         
75 Spring Street, S.W., Suite 1176
Atlanta, GA  30303
Tel.:  (404) 331-7100                         





 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    