
    <document>
        <title>Motion for Entry of Proposed Final
Judgment and Memorandum in Support</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in three
formats: this web page (for browsing content), PDF (comparable to original document formatting), and 
 WordPerfect. To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 









THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA 







UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,    
         
       
Plaintiff,

            
                v. 
              ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and   
                BOWATER INC.,
                                
                Defendants. 




    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
              |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          

 CASE NO: 1:07-cv-1912 
              JUDGE: Collyer, Rosemary M. 
              
DECK TYPE: Antitrust 
              DATE STAMP:
            



MOTION FOR ENTRY OF PROPOSED FINAL JUDGMENT 
          AND
          MEMORANDUM IN SUPPORT
 Pursuant to Section 2(e)-(f) of the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties 
          Act (the "APPA" or "Tunney Act"), 15 U.S.C. §16(e)-(f), with the 
          consent of the Defendants, the United States moves for entry of the 
          proposed Final Judgment (copy attached) in this civil antitrust action. 
        I.  The United States and the Defendants have 
          complied with the APPA
 Simultaneously with this motion, the United States is filing a Certificate 
          of Compliance certifying that the parties have complied with all applicable 
          provisions of the APPA, and that the waiting periods imposed by the 
          APPA have expired. The APPA prescribes a sixty-day period following 
          publication of notice in the Federal Register for the submission of 
          comments. 15 U.S.C. §§ 16(b) and (d). The APPA also prescribes 
          a sixty day waiting period following commencement of publication in 
          a local newspaper before the Judgment may be entered. 15 U.S.C. 
          § 16(c). Notice of the proposed Final Judgment was published in 
          the Federal Register on November 8, 2007. Thus the sixty-day comment 
          period ended on February 7, 2008. Notice of the proposed Final Judgment 
          was published in a local newspaper, The Washington Post, starting 
          on November 18, 2007 and ending on November 24, 2007. The United States 
          received one comment, a 22 page document with over 200 pages of attachments 
          from the Newspaper Association of America ("NAA") on January 2, 2008. 
          The United States responded to this comment on April 18, 2008 and published 
          the NAA's Comment, its attachments and the Response of the United States 
          in the Federal Register on June 10, 2008.(1) 
          See 15 U.S.C. § 16(d)(noting that the United States shall file 
          comments with the district court and publish them in the Federal Register.) 
          The Court may now enter the Final Judgment, which is attached to this 
          Motion. 
        II. The Proposed Final Judgment Satisfies the "Public Interest" 
          Standard
 The United States has previously filed a Competitive Impact Statement 
          ("CIS"). In that CIS, the United States explained that entry of the 
          proposed Final Judgment is in the public interest because it remedies 
          the Defendants' violations alleged in the Complaint, prevents recurrence 
          of those violations, and preserves competition in the relevant market. 
          The public, including affected competitors and customers, has now had 
          an opportunity to comment on the proposed Final Judgment as required 
          by statute. 
         Before entering the proposed Final Judgment, the Court must determine 
          whether the Judgment "is in the public interest," see U.S.C. § 
          16(e). In making that determination, the Court shall consider: 
         (A) the competitive impact of such judgment, including termination 
          of alleged violations, provisions for enforcement and modification, 
          duration of relief sought, anticipated effects of alternative remedies 
          actually considered, whether its terms are ambiguous, and any other 
          competitive considerations bearing upon the adequacy of such judgment 
          that the court deems necessary to a determination of whether the consent 
          judgment is in the public interest; and ' 
         (B) the impact of entry of such judgment upon competition in the relevant 
          market or markets, upon the public generally and individuals alleging 
          specific injury from the violations set forth in the complaint including 
          consideration of the public benefit, if any, to be derived from a determination 
          of the issues at trial. 
15 U.S.C. § 16(3). 
         In its CIS, the United States described the meaning and proper application 
          of the public interest standard under the APPA and now incorporates 
          those statements herein by reference. The public, including affected 
          competitors and customers, has had the opportunity to comment on the 
          proposed Final Judgment as required by law. The NAA filed the only comment. 
          The United States filed its Response to Public Comments on the proposed 
          Final Judgment, which explains why that the proposed Final Judgment 
          is within the range of settlements consistent with the public interest. 
        
III. Conclusion
 For the reasons set forth in this Memorandum and in the CIS, the Court 
          should find that the proposed Final Judgment is in the public interest. 
          The Court should then enter the proposed Final Judgment.  
        

Dated: June 18, 2008
     
                              Respectfully submitted,





  
 ____/s/___Karl D. Knutsen___
              Karl D. Knutsen, Esq. 
              Ryan Danks, Esq. 
              Rebecca A. Perlmutter, Esq. 
              Michelle Seltzer, Esq. (D.C. Bar No. 475482) 
              U.S. Department of Justice, Antitrust Division 
              1401 H St., N.W., Suite 4000 
              Washington, DC 20530 
              T: (202) 514-0976 
              F: (202) 307-5802 




FOOTNOTES

1.  The United States wishes to correct a statement 
          it made in its Response to Public Comments submitted on April 18, 2008. 
          As an example of swings in pricing based on changes in input costs and 
          industry capacity, the United States stated that newsprint prices were 
          at or below the lowest level which prices reached in 2006. Response 
          of Plaintiff United States to Public Comments on the Proposed Final 
          Judgment, at 11-15. That statement was made based on industry information 
          available as of the date of the filing. Since that filing, data released 
          for the entire month of April indicate that the average newsprint prices 
          for April 2008 were one to two percent higher than they were at the 
          lowest point of 2006. 
      


 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    