
    <document>
        <title>Complaint</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Aetna and The Prudential Insurance 
            Company</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in two
formats: this web page (for browsing content) and PDF (comparable to original document formatting). To view the PDF you will need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the
Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 








UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
	FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF TEXAS
	(DALLAS DIVISION)









UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, and the  
STATE OF TEXAS,             
           
 
Plaintiffs,



            
                v.    

AETNA INC., and		
THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE COMPANY OF AMERICA,  
                    								
     
                          

 Defendants.





    |
    |
    |  
    |
            |
            |
            |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


Civil Action No.: 
              3-99 CV 398-H
	Filed: June 21, 1999
    




      COMPLAINT

        The United States of America, acting under the direction of the Attorney 
        General of the United States, and the State of Texas, acting under the 
        direction of the Texas Attorney General, bring this action to enjoin defendant 
        Aetna, Inc. ("Aetna") from acquiring certain health insurance-related 
        assets of its competitor, defendant The Prudential Insurance Company of 
        America ("Prudential"), in violation of Section 7 of the Clayton 
        Act, as amended, 15 U.S.C. § 18, and alleges as follows: 
      1.          Aetna is the largest health insurance company in the United States, providing   health
care benefits to approximately 15.8 million people in 50 states and the District of   Columbia. 
Prudential is the ninth largest health insurance company in the nation, providing   health care
benefits to approximately 4.9 million people in 28 states and the District of   Columbia.
2.          Aetna and Prudential each offer a wide range of managed health insurance plans,  
including health maintenance organization ("HMO") plans and point of service ("POS") plans.   
Aetna and Prudential compete against each other in part by offering HMO and HMO-based POS  
("HMO-POS") plans in Houston and Dallas, Texas, providing consumers with increased quality  
and lower prices for HMO and HMO-POS plans in those areas.  Aetna's acquisition of Prudential 
 will eliminate the direct competition between them and will give Aetna the ability to increase  
prices paid for these products or to reduce their quality in Houston and Dallas.
      3. In addition, Aetna and Prudential purchase physician services for their 
        health plan members. Aetna's acquisition of Prudential will consolidate 
        their purchasing power and will give Aetna the ability to depress physicians' 
        reimbursement rates in Houston and Dallas, which is likely to lead to 
        a reduction in the quantity or a degradation in the quality of physician 
        services provided to patients in those areas.
        
I.
 JURISDICTION AND VENUE
4.          This Complaint is filed pursuant to Section 15 and 16 of the Clayton
Act, as   amended, 15 U.S.C. §§ 25 and 26, to prevent and restrain the defendants'
violation of Section 7   of the Clayton Act, as amended, 15 U.S.C. § 18.
5.       Aetna and Prudential are engaged in interstate commerce and in activities   substantially
affecting interstate commerce.
6.       This Court has subject matter jurisdiction over this action and jurisdiction over the  
parties pursuant to Section 12 of the Clayton Act, 15 U.S.C. § 22, and 28 U.S.C.
§§ 1331 and   1337(a).
7.        Venue is proper in this District under 15 U.S.C. § 22 and 28 U.S.C. §
1391(c), in   that each of the defendants is a corporation that transacts business and is found in
the Northern   District of Texas.

     II.     THE DEFENDANTS
8.        Aetna is a Connecticut corporation with its principal place of business
in Hartford,   Connecticut.  Aetna is a leading provider of health and retirement benefits and
financial services.    Aetna's subsidiary, Aetna U.S. Healthcare, offers an array of health
insurance products,   including indemnity ("fee for service"), preferred provider organization
("PPO"), POS, and   HMO plans.  In 1998, Aetna U.S. Healthcare had revenues of over $14
billion.
9.        Prudential is a New Jersey mutual life insurance company with its principal place   of
business in Newark, New Jersey.  The Prudential HealthCare Plan, Inc. ("Prudential  
HealthCare"), a Texas corporation, is a wholly owned subsidiary of PRUCO, Inc., which is itself  
a wholly owned subsidiary of Prudential.  Prudential HealthCare offers HMO, POS, PPO, and  
indemnity plans.  In 1998, Prudential HealthCare reported total revenues of about $7.5 billion.

   III.    THE PROPOSED ACQUISITION
10.        Aetna and Aetna Life Insurance Company, a Connecticut life
insurance company   and wholly owned subsidiary of Aetna, entered into the Asset Transfer and
Acquisition   Agreement (the "Agreement") with Prudential and PRUCO, Inc., dated as of
December 9, 1998,   for the purchase of substantially all of Prudential's assets related to the
business of issuing,   selling, and administering group medical and dental indemnity and
managed care plans.
11.        The stated purchase price in the Agreement is $1 billion, consisting of $465   million
in cash, $500 million in three-year promissory notes, $15 million in cash payable under a  
Coinsurance Agreement, and $20 million in cash to be paid under the Risk-Sharing Agreement.
12.        The proposed transaction is part of a trend towards increasing consolidation   among
health insurance companies.  Aetna itself has made a number of acquisitions over the past   few
years.  It purchased U.S. Healthcare, Inc. in July 1996 and NYLCare Health Plans, Inc. in   July
1998.

   IV. REDUCTION IN COMPETITION IN THE   SALE OF HMO AND HMO-POS
PLANS
13.          Managed care companies, such as Aetna and Prudential, contract
with employers and other group   purchasers to provide health insurance services or to administer
health care coverage provided to   employees and group members.  For managed care companies
to attract substantial enrollment,   they must offer networks composed of a variety of health care
providers (i.e., physicians,   hospitals, and other health care professionals and facilities) within a
local area.  Employees who   obtain health plan coverage for themselves and their families from
these companies receive   access to a provider network that offers them a menu of physician and
hospital options for   medical treatment.
14.     To control the cost of health care services provided to employees, managed care  
companies contract with health care providers to provide health care services covered by the plan 
 at an agreed-upon rate, subject to certain utilization review and management requirements.   
Managed care products, including HMO, PPO and POS plans, have become increasingly popular 
 options for employers, largely because of the managed care companies' ability to obtain  
competitive rates from health care providers and to control utilization, allowing them to offer  
more affordable health insurance than traditional indemnity plans.
15.        While each type of managed care plan offers a network of providers, the types of  
plans differ by structure, price, licensing requirements, and benefit configurations.  Thus, for  
example, HMOs provide better benefits with respect to health maintenance or preventative care,  
but they place greater limits on treatment options, restrict access to out-of-network providers, and 
 use a primary care physician as a "gatekeeper" to control access to specialty care.  In contrast,  
PPO plans do not emphasize health maintenance or preventative care, but they put fewer  
restrictions on utilization, provide some reimbursement for out-of-network services, and permit  
self-referral to network specialists without using a gatekeeper.  As a result, PPO plans are  
generally more expensive than HMOs.  POS plans can be based on either an HMO or PPO  
network and generally fall between HMO and PPO plans in terms of access and cost.  That is,  
POS plans offer patients greater access to health care providers and cost more than HMO plans,  
but they generally do not provide as much access or cost as much as PPO plans.
16.        Managed care companies compete to be chosen by employers by developing and  
selling health insurance plans primarily on the basis of the breadth and quality of their provider  
networks, the level of  benefits provided to employees, and their price (including premiums,  
deductibles, copayments, and coinsurance).

    Relevant Product Market

17.        By virtue of the benefit design differences, pricing differentials, and other factors,  
PPOs and indemnity plans are not reasonable substitutes for HMO and HMO-POS products.   
Neither employers nor employees view HMOs and PPOs as the same product, and enrollees who  
leave an HMO disproportionately select another HMO, rather than a PPO, for their next plan.
18.        A small but significant increase in the price of HMO and HMO-POS products   would
not cause a sufficient number of customers to shift to other health insurance products to   make
such a price increase unprofitable.  HMO and HMO-POS plans, therefore, are an   appropriate
relevant product market within which to assess the likely effects of the proposed  
acquisition.
 
            Relevant
   Geographic Market

19.        Patients seeking medical care generally prefer to receive treatment close to where  
they work or live, and many employers require managed care companies to offer a network that  
contains a certain number of health care providers within a specified distance of each employee's  
home.  As a result, virtually all managed care companies establish provider networks in the  
localities where employees live and work, and they compete on the basis of their local provider  
networks.  The relevant geographic markets in which HMO and HMO-POS health plans compete 
 are thus no larger than the local areas within which managed care companies market their  
respective HMO and HMO-POS plans.
20.        The relevant geographic markets for which relief is sought here are the United   States
Department of Commerce Metropolitan Statistical Areas ("MSAs") in and around   Houston and
Dallas, Texas.  In Houston, the geographic market consists of an area no larger than   the
following counties: Brazoria, Chambers, Fort Bend, Galveston, Harris, Liberty, Montgomery,  
and Waller counties.  In Dallas, the geographic market consists of an area no larger than the  
following counties: Collin, Dallas, Denton, Ellis, Grayson, Henderson, Hood, Hunt, Johnson,  
Kaufman, Parker, Rockwall, and Tarrant counties.  A small but significant increase in the price  
of HMO and HMO-POS products in these two geographic areas would not cause a sufficient  
number of customers to switch to health plans outside of these areas to make such a price  
increase unprofitable.  The Houston and Dallas areas are, therefore, the relevant geographic  
markets within which to assess the likely effects of the proposed acquisition.
 
          
     Concentration, Entry, and Expansion 

21.        Aetna and Prudential are among each other's principal competitors in the HMO   and
HMO-POS markets in Houston and Dallas, and are considered by employers to be close  
substitutes in their product attributes and quality.
22.       In Houston, Aetna currently has 44% of the HMO and HMO-POS enrollees, and  
Prudential has 19%.  (Aetna's share of HMO and HMO-POS enrollees increased from 13% to  
44% with its purchase of NYLCare.)  After the merger, Aetna will have 63%.  In Dallas, Aetna  
currently has 26% of the HMO and HMO-POS enrollees, and Prudential has 16%.  (Aetna's  
share of HMO and HMO-POS enrollees increased from 11% to 26% with the NYLCare  
transaction.)  After the merger, Aetna will have 42%.
23.        For managed care companies, the costs in time and money of setting up HMO   and
HMO-POS plans (e.g., licensing costs, network construction costs, and utilization   management
costs) are substantially higher than those required for setting up PPO or indemnity   plans. 
Effective entry -- entry and growth to minimum viable scale -- for an HMO or HMO-POS   plan
in either Houston or Dallas typically takes two to three years and costs up to $50 million.  It   is
unlikely that de novo entry would defeat a price increase over the short term in these areas.  It   is
also unlikely that a company that currently provides PPO or indemnity health insurance in  
either Dallas or Houston would shift its resources to provide an HMO or HMO-POS plan in  
either of these geographic markets in the event of a small but significant price increase, because  
of the costs and difficulties of doing so.
24.        Due not only to these costs and difficulties, but also to advantages that Aetna and  
Prudential hold over their existing competitors -- including nationally recognized quality  
accreditation, product array, provider network and national scope and reputation -- existing HMO 
 and HMO-POS competitors in Dallas or Houston are unlikely to be able to expand or reposition  
themselves sufficiently to restrain anticompetitive conduct by Aetna in either of these geographic 
 markets.
25.       For these reasons, neither entry by new sellers nor expansion by existing sellers  
would be timely, likely, or sufficient to counteract an anticompetitive price increase.
  

   Effects of the Proposed Transaction 

26.    The existing competition between Aetna and Prudential in providing HMO and     
HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas has benefitted consumers through lower prices and  
increased quality of such plans in those areas.  Aetna's acquisition of Prudential would eliminate  
this competition, allowing the merged entity to increase the prices and to reduce the quality of  
these products in Houston and Dallas.


 V.
 CONSOLIDATION OF PURCHASING POWER 
          OVER PHYSICIAN SERVICES 
 
  Relevant          Product Market

27.        There are no purchasers to whom physicians can sell their services other than  
individual patients or the commercial and government health insurers who purchase physician  
services on their behalf.  Simply put, physicians have no good alternatives to these buyers.  A  
small but significant decrease in the prices paid to physicians by these buyers would not cause  
physicians to seek other purchasers of their services or to otherwise change their activities (away  
from providing physician services towards other uses or leisure) in numbers sufficient to make  
such a price reduction unprofitable.  Physicians' services, therefore, also constitute an appropriate 
 relevant product market within which to assess the likely effects of the proposed transaction.
    Relevant 
      
   Geographic Market

28.        The patient preferences that define a localized geographic market for the sale of  
HMO and HMO-POS products also define a localized geographic market for physicians'  
services.  Moreover, for an established physician who has invested time and expense in building  
a practice, the costs associated with moving his or her practice to a new geographic market are  
considerable, including paying for new office space and equipment and building new  
relationships with hospitals, other physicians, employees, and patients in the new area.
29.        A small but significant decrease in the prices paid to physicians would not cause  
physicians to relocate their practices outside of the Houston and Dallas markets in numbers  
sufficient to make such a price reduction unprofitable.  Similarly, a reduction in the quantity or  
quality of physician services as a result of a small but significant decrease in the prices paid to  
physicians would not cause patients to seek physicians' services outside of these markets, in  
numbers sufficient to make such a price reduction unprofitable.  The relevant geographic markets 
 within which to assess the likely effects of the proposed acquisition on the sale of physician  
services are, therefore, no larger than the geographic markets described in paragraph 20, above. 

     Effects of the Proposed Transaction
      30.       The contract terms a physician can obtain from a managed care company such as 
 Aetna or Prudential depend on the physician's ability to terminate (or credibly to threaten to  
terminate) their relationship if the company demands unfavorable contract terms.  A physician's  
ability to terminate a provider relationship depends on the ability to make up that plan's lost  
business and on how long it would take to do so.  Unlike certain tangible products, physician  
services cannot be stored; therefore, failing to replace lost business expeditiously imposes a  
permanent loss of revenue.
31.    Physicians have a limited ability to encourage patients to switch plans or   physicians,
because the patients would have to switch to another employer-sponsored plan in   which the
physicians participate (which might not be an option), or to pay considerably higher  
out-of-pocket costs, either in the form of increased copayments for use of out-of-network  
physicians (if allowed), or by absorbing the total cost of the physicians' services as   
unreimbursed medical expenses.
32.  Replacing a discontinued plan's lost business in a timely manner is more difficult   when
the plan accounts for a large share of the physician's total business.  Aetna's "all products  
clause" -- which requires a physician to participate in all of Aetna's health plans if he or she  
participates in any Aetna plan -- significantly increases the volume of business that a physician  
would lose if he or she rejected Aetna's offered reimbursement rates on any given plan, such as  
an HMO.  Terminating the provider relationship thus would mean that a physician not only  
would lose his or her own patients that participated in that plan, but also access to other patients  
who participate in the plan.  Replacing lost business in a timely manner is more difficult when  
the managed care company accounts for a large share of all business in that locality (not only of  
that physician's business), because a physician's alternative sources of patients are more limited.
33.       As a result of Aetna's prior acquisition of NYLCare and its proposed acquisition   of
Prudential, Aetna will account for a large share of all payments to physicians in the Houston  
and Dallas areas, and a particularly large share of revenue of individual physicians for a  
substantial number of physicians in those areas.  In light of physicians' limited ability to  
encourage patient switching, a significant number of physicians will be unable to reject Aetna's  
demands for contract terms that are more adverse than would result if Aetna and Prudential  
remained independent.  Thus, the proposed acquisition will give Aetna the ability to depress  
physicians' reimbursement rates in Houston and Dallas, likely leading to a reduction in quantity  
or degradation in quality of physicians' services.

   VI.   VIOLATIONS ALLEGED
34.        Aetna's proposed acquisition of Prudential may substantially lessen
competition   in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS products and will consolidate purchasing
power over   physician services in Houston and Dallas, Texas, in violation of Section 7 of the
Clayton Act.
35.        Unless enjoined, the transaction will eliminate competition between Aetna and  
Prudential, and likely have the effects in the Houston and Dallas geographic markets of :



substantially lessening competition in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS    products, and
increasing prices for or decreasing the quality of these    products; and


giving Aetna the ability to depress 
                physicians' reimbursement rates, which is likely to lead to a 
                reduction in the quantity or a degradation in the quality of 
                physician services provided to patients.



VII.
 REQUESTED RELIEF 




WHEREFORE, plaintiffs, the United States of America and the State 
        of Texas, request: 
      


That the proposed acquisition by Aetna and Prudential be adjudged 
          to violate Section 7 of the Clayton Act, as amended, 15 U.S.C. § 
          18; 
          

That the defendants be permanently enjoined from and restrained from 
          carrying out the Asset Transfer and Acquisition Agreement dated as of 
          December 9, 1998, or from entering into or carrying out any agreements, 
          understanding, or plan, the purpose or effect of which would be to combine 
          the health insurance businesses or assets of Aetna and Prudential; 
          

That plaintiffs have such other relief as this Court may deem just 
          and proper; and 
          

That plaintiffs recover the costs of this action. 
          



      DATED this 21st day of June, 1999.



 FOR PLAINTIFF 
            UNITED STATES OF AMERICA 
_______________/s/________________
              JOEL I. KLEIN 
              Assistant Attorney General 
_______________/s/________________
              DONNA PATTERSON 
              Deputy Assistant Attorney General 
_______________/s/________________
              CONSTANCE K. ROBINSON 
              Director of Operations and 
              Merger Enforcement 
_______________/s/________________
              SUSAN M. DAVIES 
              Senior Counsel 
_______________/s/________________
              GAIL KURSH, Chief 
              Health Care Task Force 
_______________/s/________________
              DAVID C. JORDAN, Assistant Chief
              Health Care Task Force 
_______________/s/________________
              PAUL J. O'DONNELL 
              JOHN B. ARNETT, SR. 
              STEVEN BRODSKY 
              DEBORAH A. BROWN 
              CLAUDIA H. DULMAGE 
              DIONNE C. LOMAX 
              FREDERICK S. YOUNG 
Attorneys 
              U.S. Department of Justice 
              Antitrust Division
              Health Care Task Force
              325 Seventh St. N.W., Suite 400
              Washington, D.C. 20530
              Tel: (202) 616-5933
              Facsimile: (202) 514-1517 

                
               
 FOR PLAINTIFF
            THE STATE OF TEXAS
JOHN CORNYN
              Texas Attorney General
ANDY TAYLOR
              First Assistant Attorney General
LINDA S. EADS
              Deputy Attorney General
              for Litigation 
            DAVID A. TALBOT, JR. 
              Assistant Attorney General
              Chief, Consumer Protection Division
_______________/s/________________
              MARK TOBEY 
              Assistant Attorney General
              Chief, Antitrust Section 
              State Bar No. 20082960 
              Office of the Attorney General
              P.O. Box 12548 
              Austin, Texas 78711-2548
              Tel: (512) 463-2185 
              Facsimile: (512) 320-0975 








 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    