
    <document>
        <title>Joint Rule 11 Memorandum</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. ABB Middle East & Africa Participations 
            AG</case_name>
        <text>


  

This document is available in two formats: this web page (for browsing content) and 
PDF (comparable to original
document formatting). To view the PDF you will need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group.  











IN THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
     FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF ALABAMA
     SOUTHERN DIVISION







UNITED STATES OF AMERICA           


            
                v.    

ABB MIDDLE EAST & AFRICA
 PARTICIPATIONS AG,
            
                           
   Defendant.




    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


Criminal No. CR-01-N-135-S

Filed: April 11, 2001

Violation: 15 U.S.C. § 1            
    



JOINT RULE 11 MEMORANDUM
  The United States and defendant ABB MIDDLE EAST & AFRICA
PARTICIPATIONS AG ("ABB MEA") submit this memorandum to set forth the
factual basis for the parties' plea agreement pursuant to Rule 11(f) of the Federal
Rules of Criminal Procedure.  Pursuant to the plea agreement, ABB MEA has
waived indictment and will plead guilty to the captioned one-count Information
charging ABB MEA with violating the Sherman Act, 15 U.S.C. § 1.  The United
States and ABB MEA have entered into a plea agreement pursuant to Rule
11(e)(1)(C) of the Federal Rules of Criminal Procedure.  This memorandum provides
the Court with sufficient information for acceptance of the plea by setting forth the
statute violated, a statement of facts supporting the plea agreement, and the terms
of the plea agreement.


I
STATUTE VIOLATED
A.     The Sherman Act
The Information charges ABB MEA with one count of bid rigging in violation
of the Sherman Act, 15 U.S.C. § 1.  Section One of Title 15, United States Code,
provides:

Every contract, combination in the form of trust or otherwise, or
conspiracy, in restraint of trade or commerce among the several
States, or with foreign nations, is hereby declared to be illegal. 
Every person who shall make any contract or engage in any
combination or conspiracy hereby declared to be illegal shall be
deemed guilty of a felony, and, on conviction thereof, shall be
punished by fine not exceeding $10,000,000 if a corporation, or,
if any other person, $350,000, or by imprisonment not exceeding
three years, or by both said punishments, in the discretion of the
court.
The Information charges that beginning at least as early as June 1989 and
continuing until at least September 20, 1996, ABB MEA and others participated in
a conspiracy to suppress and eliminate competition by rigging the bids on Contract
29, a wastewater construction contract funded by the United States Agency for
International Development ("USAID") and performed in the Arab Republic of
Egypt. 

B.     Elements of the Offense
  The elements of a Sherman Act offense, each of which the United States must
prove beyond a reasonable doubt, are:


  the conspiracy charged was formed, and it was in existence at or about
the time alleged;

  the defendant knowingly formed or participated in that conspiracy;
and

  the activity that was the object of the conspiracy was within the flow
of, or substantially affected, interstate or foreign commerce.

C.     Maximum Penalty
  The maximum penalty ABB MEA may receive upon its conviction in this case
is a fine in an amount equal to the largest of:  (a) $10 million; (b) twice the gross
pecuniary gain derived from the crime; or (c) twice the gross pecuniary loss caused
to the victims of the crime. 

II
FACTUAL BASIS
  This statement of facts is intended to be used as a factual basis for the guilty
plea of ABB MEA.  It is not intended to present all details surrounding the charged
conspiracy.
A.     Background
  As a result of the Camp David Peace Accords in the late 1970s, the United
States and other Western countries committed to fund extensive rehabilitation
work on the water treatment and disposal facilities in the Arab Republic of Egypt. 
Pursuant to this commitment, USAID, an agency of the United States government,
funded nearly a billion dollars in work by U.S. construction companies in the 1980s
and early 1990s.  The USAID-funded contracts were designed to be awarded to
prequalified United States contractors on the basis of competitive sealed bids.  ABB
MEA's conduct in this case affected Contract 29, a $134.775 million contract
awarded to its affiliate, SAE Sadelmi USA, Inc.

B.     The Conspiracy
  Beginning at least as early as June 1989 and continuing until at least
September 20, 1996, competitors for the USAID-funded contracts in Egypt entered
into and participated in a combination and conspiracy to suppress and eliminate
competition by rigging the bids on Contract 29.  The conspiracy consisted of a
continuing agreement, understanding, and concert of action among ABB MEA and
its co-conspirators to rig the bids to ensure that SAE Sadelmi USA, Inc. won
Contract 29.  ABB MEA sought to guarantee that SAE Sadelmi USA, Inc. would be
awarded the contract by agreeing with co-conspirators that they would submit an
artificially inflated bid on Contract 29 in exchange for payment of $3.4 million.

  For the purpose of forming and carrying out the charged combination and
conspiracy, ABB MEA and its co-conspirators did those things that they combined
and conspired to do, including, among other things:


  participating in meetings and conversations to discuss rigging
the bids on Contract 29; 

  agreeing, during those meetings and conversations, to bid at
certain levels and otherwise to increase the price level of bids on
Contract 29; 

  agreeing, during those meetings and conversations, to suppress
or eliminate competition on Contract 29; 

  agreeing, during those meetings and conversations, that ABB
MEA, or an affiliate company, would compensate co-conspirators
by a $3.4 million payment, in exchange for the submission of an
artificially inflated bid on Contract 29; 

  issuing bid tenders on Contract 29 in accordance with the
agreement reached; and

  receiving payment on Contract 29 from USAID.

C.     Interstate and Foreign Commerce and Venue
  Contract 29, the USAID-funded contract in the Arab Republic of Egypt that
is the subject of the charged conspiracy, involved a substantial amount of
commerce.  The business of the conspirators in bidding on and performing this
contract was in a continuous and uninterrupted flow of, and substantially affected,
interstate and foreign commerce.   Acts in connection with the bidding on Contract
29, and in furtherance of the bid-rigging conspiracy, occurred in the Northern
District of Alabama.

 III
PLEA AGREEMENT
ABB MEA will enter a guilty plea in this case pursuant to a plea agreement
between ABB MEA and the United States.  The plea agreement provides that ABB
MEA will enter a plea of guilty pursuant to Rule 11(e)(1)(C) of the Federal Rules of
Criminal Procedure to a one-count criminal Information charging that from at least
as early as June 1989 and continuing until at least September 20, 1996, ABB MEA
and others entered into and engaged in a conspiracy to rig bids on Contract 29, a
USAID-funded construction contract performed in the Arab Republic of Egypt, in
violation of 15 U.S.C. § 1.  The plea agreement and the Information have been filed
in the Northern District of Alabama, where certain acts in furtherance of the
conspiracy took place.

  Also pursuant to the plea agreement, the United States and ABB MEA agree
jointly to recommend that the Court impose a sentence requiring ABB MEA to pay
a fine to the United States in an amount of fifty-three million dollars ($53,000,000),
pursuant to 18 U.S.C. § 3571(d).  The fine shall be payable in installments over five
years without interest, in accordance with 18 U.S.C. § 3612(h) and U.S.S.G. 
§ 8C3.2(b).(1)  Should the Court reject the
agreed-upon disposition of the case, ABB
MEA will be free to withdraw its plea.  The United States and ABB MEA also
jointly request that the Court accept ABB MEA's guilty plea and immediately
impose sentence on the day of arraignment pursuant to Fed. R. Crim. P. 32(b)(1)
and U.S.S.G. § 6A1.1.(2)
  ABB MEA and its parent organization, subsidiaries, and affiliates have
agreed to cooperate fully with the United States in the conduct of the present
criminal investigation of bid rigging on USAID-funded construction contracts in
Egypt and any resulting criminal litigation or other criminal proceedings to which
the United States is a party.  Such cooperation includes, but is not limited to, the
production of relevant documents under the control of ABB MEA and its parent
organization, subsidiaries, and affiliates.  ABB MEA and its parent organization,
subsidiaries, and affiliates will also use their best efforts to secure, in connection
with the present criminal investigation and any resulting criminal litigation, the
full and truthful cooperation of any current or former directors, officers, and
employees, who are identified by the United States as possessing information
relevant to its criminal investigation.  Such cooperation includes testifying
truthfully in criminal trial and grand jury proceedings.

  Pursuant to the plea agreement, the United States agrees, subject to the
continuing full cooperation of ABB MEA and its parent company, not to bring
further criminal proceedings against ABB MEA and its parent organization,
subsidiaries, and affiliates for any act or offense committed prior to the date of the
plea agreement in connection with the conspiracy to rig the bids on USAID-funded
construction projects in the Arab Republic of Egypt.  Subject to their continuing
cooperation, the directors, officers, and employees of ABB MEA and its parent
organization, subsidiaries, and affiliates, with the exception of Eberhard 
VonKoerber, former member of the parent company's executive committee, will
receive the same protection against prosecution. 

Dated: April 11, 2001






   
     
                              Respectfully submitted,






                       
/S/                       
____________________________________
MAX ABITBOL, President         
ABB MIDDLE EAST & AFRICA  
 PARTICIPATIONS AG               
                              
                              
                       
/S/             
____________________________________
GORDON L. LANG            
LESLIE P. MACHADO              
Counsel for ABB MIDDLE 
EAST & AFRICA PARTICIPATIONS AG 


                       
/S/                             
_______________________________
WILLIAM D. DILLON
JON R. SMIBERT
     
Attorneys, U.S. Department of Justice
Antitrust Division
Richard B. Russell Building
75 Spring St., S.W., Suite 1176
Atlanta, GA 30303
Tel.: (404) 331-7100                                




FOOTNOTES

1.  ABB MEA has also agreed to make restitution to USAID in the
amount of
ten million dollars.
2.  The parties agree that sentencing can proceed without a
presentence report.





 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    