
    <document>
        <title>Competitive Impact Statement</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Aetna and The Prudential Insurance 
            Company</case_name>
        <text>





This document is available 
          in two formats: this web page (for browsing content) and PDF 
          (comparable to original document formatting). To view the PDF you will 
          need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe 
          site. For an official signed copy, please contact the Antitrust 
          Documents Group. 










UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURT
FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF TEXAS
(DALLAS DIVISION)








UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, and the           				
STATE OF TEXAS,               
           
Plaintiffs,


            
                v.    

AETNA INC., and									
THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE COMPANY OF AMERICA,
            
                           
Defendants.




	    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


Civil Action No.:3-99CV1398-H


Judge Sanders                  

    





COMPETITIVE IMPACT STATEMENT

Pursuant to Section 2(b) of the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act
("APPA"), 15
U.S.C. § 16(b)-(h), the United States submits this Competitive Impact Statement to assist
the
Court in assessing the Proposed Final Judgement submitted for entry
in this civil antitrust
proceeding.

 I.
NATURE AND
PURPOSE OF THIS PROCEEDING
The
United States filed a civil antitrust Complaint under Section 15 of the
Clayton Act,
15 U.S.C. §25, on June 21, 1999, alleging that the proposed acquisition by Aetna
Inc.
("Aetna")
of The Prudential Insurance Company of America's ("Prudential") health care business
would
violate Section 7 of the Clayton Act ("Section 7"), 15 U.S.C. § 18.  The State of
Texas,
by and
through its Attorney General, is co-plaintiff with the United States in this action.
The
Complaint alleges that Aetna and Prudential compete head-to-head in the sale of
health maintenance organization ("HMO") and HMO-based point-of-service
("HMO-POS")
health plans in Houston and Dallas, Texas; that such competition has benefitted consumers
by
keeping prices low and quality high; and that the proposed acquisition would end such
competition and give Aetna sufficient market power to increase prices or reduce quality in
the
sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans in these geographic areas.  (Complaint ¶ 26.) 
The
Complaint
also alleges that the acquisition would enable Aetna to unduly depress physicians'
reimbursement rates in Houston and Dallas, resulting in a reduction of quantity or a
degradation
in quality of physicians' services in these areas.  (Complaint ¶ 33.)
When
the Complaint was filed, the plaintiffs also filed a proposed settlement that would
permit Aetna to complete its acquisition of Prudential but would require divestitures of
certain
assets sufficient to preserve competition in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans and the
purchase of physicians' services in Houston and Dallas.  This settlement consists of a
proposed
Final Judgment,  Hold Separate Stipulation and Order, and Stipulation.



The
proposed Final Judgment requires Aetna to divest its interests in the Houston-area
commercial HMO and HMO-POS businesses of NYLCare Health Plans of the Gulf Coast,
Inc.
("NYLCare-Gulf Coast"), a previously acquired health plan serving Houston and other areas
in
south and central Texas, and the commercial HMO and HMO-POS businesses of
NYLCare
Health Plans of the Southwest, Inc. ("NYLCare-Southwest"), a previously acquired health
plan
serving the Dallas area.  If Aetna does not complete the divestitures within the time frame
established in the proposed Final Judgment, a trustee appointed by the Court will be
empowered
to sell NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest.  If the assets are not sold within six
(6)
months after the appointment of the trustee, the Court shall enter such orders as it shall
deem
appropriate to carry out the purpose of the trust.  (Final Judgment ¶ V.A., F.)


The
Hold Separate Stipulation and Order ensures that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and
NYLCare-Southwest function as independent, economically viable, ongoing business
concerns
and that competition is maintained prior to the divestitures.  It requires Aetna to take steps
to
immediately preserve, maintain, and operate NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest
as
independent competitors with management, sales, service, underwriting, administration,
and
operations held entirely separate, distinct, and apart from those of Aetna. Until the
plaintiffs, in
their sole discretion, determine that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest can
function
as effective competitors, Aetna may not take any action to consummate the proposed
acquisition
of Prudential.1 
(Final Judgment ¶ IV.H.)


The
United States, the State of Texas, and the defendants have stipulated that the
proposed Final Judgment may be entered after compliance with the APPA.  Entry of the
proposed Final Judgment would terminate this action, except that the Court would retain
jurisdiction to construe, modify, or enforce the provisions of the proposed Final Judgment and
to
punish violations thereof.

II.
THE ALLEGED
VIOLATIONS


A. The Defendants


Aetna
is a Connecticut corporation providing health and retirement benefits and financial
services with its principal place of business in Hartford, Connecticut.  Through its wholly
owned
subsidiary, Aetna U.S. Healthcare, Aetna offers an array of health insurance products,
including
indemnity ("fee-for-service"), preferred provider organization ("PPO"), POS, and HMO
plans.
Aetna also purchases physicians' services for its health plan members, which it offers to
members through Aetna's health plans.  In 1998, Aetna U.S. Healthcare reported revenues
of
over $14 billion and was the largest health insurance company in the country, providing
health
care benefits to approximately 15.8 million people in 50 states and the District of
Columbia.


Prudential is a New Jersey mutual life insurance company with its principal
place of
business in Newark, New Jersey.  Like Aetna, Prudential offers indemnity, PPO, POS, and
HMO plans and also buys physicians' services, which it offers to its enrollees through
Prudential's health plans.  In 1998, Prudential HealthCare reported total revenues of
approximately $7.5 billion and was the nation's ninth largest health insurance company,
serving
approximately 4.9 million health insurance beneficiaries in 28 states and the District of
Columbia.


B. Description of the Events Giving Rise to the Alleged Violations


Aetna
and Aetna Life Insurance Company, a wholly owned subsidiary of Aetna, entered
into an Asset Transfer and Acquisition Agreement ("Agreement") dated December 9, 1998,
with
Prudential and PRUCO, Inc., a wholly owned subsidiary of Prudential.  Under the terms of
the
Agreement, Aetna would acquire substantially all of Prudential's assets related to issuing,
selling, and administering group medical, dental indemnity, and managed care plans,
including
HMO and HMO-POS plans.  The purchase price stated in the Agreement is $1 billion,
consisting
of $465 million in cash, $500 million in three-year promissory notes, $15 million in cash
payable under a Coinsurance Agreement, and $20 million in cash to be paid under a Risk-
Sharing Agreement.

C .Anticompetitive Effects of the Proposed Acquisition


1. The Sale of HMO and HMO-POS Plans


Aetna's proposed acquisition of Prudential would be likely to substantially
lessen
competition in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas, Texas, in
violation
of Section 7.


a.Product Market


Managed care companies, such as Aetna and Prudential, contract with
employers and
other group purchasers to provide health insurance services or to administer health care
coverage
to employees and other group members.  There are a variety of managed care products
available
to employers and other group purchasers which provide health care services at an
agreed-upon
rate, subject to certain utilization review and management requirements.  These products,
which
include HMO, PPO, and POS plans, have become increasingly popular options for
employers,
largely because of the managed care companies' ability to obtain competitive rates from
health
care providers and to control utilization of health care services.


As
the Complaint alleges, HMO and HMO-POS products differ from PPO or indemnity
plans in terms of benefit design, cost, and other factors.  (Complaint ¶ 15.)  For
example,
HMOs
provide superior preventative care benefits, but they place limits on treatment options and
generally require use of a primary care physician "gatekeeper."  PPO plans, which do not
require
enrollees to go through a "gatekeeper" and do not emphasize preventative care, are
generally
more expensive than HMOs.  POS plans can be based on either an HMO or PPO network
and
fall between HMO and PPO plans in terms of access and cost.  That is, POS plans offer
patients
more flexibility at a higher cost relative to HMOs.  In general, then, PPOs and indemnity
options
are more expensive, provide better benefits with respect to coverage when ill, and allow
greater
access to providers.  In contrast, HMO and HMO-based POS options are generally less
expensive, provide better benefits with respect to health maintenance or preventative care,
place
greater limits on treatment, and restrict access to providers.  (Id.)


Not
only do these plans in fact differ by cost and benefit configuration, they are
perceived as different by purchasers; neither employers nor employees view PPO plans as
adequate substitutes for HMO or HMO-POS plans.2  Instead, they view them as distinct
products, meeting different needs and appealing to different types of enrollees.  Indeed,
enrollees
who leave an HMO disproportionately select another HMO (or HMO-POS), not a PPO, for
their
next health care benefit plan.  (Complaint ¶ 17.)


Moreover, analyses of the data obtained from the parties and from other plans
strongly
indicate that consumers -- employers and employees -- view HMO and HMO-POS plans
as
distinct from other health plans and that PPO or indemnity plans are not thought to be
ready
substitutes for HMO and HMO-POS plans.  These analyses demonstrate that the elasticity
of
demand for HMO and HMO-POS plans is sufficiently low that a small but significant
price
increase for all HMO and HMO-POS plans would be profitable because consumers would
not
shift to PPO and indemnity plans in sufficient numbers to render such an increase
unprofitable.
Together with consistent evidence from numerous witnesses interviewed,
these analyses
support the conclusion that HMO and HMO-POS plans constitute the relevant product for
analysis of the proposed transaction.  (Complaint ¶ 18.)


b.Geographic Markets


Virtually all managed care companies establish provider networks in the areas
where
employees work and live, and they compete on the basis of these local provider networks. 
The
relevant geographic markets in which HMO and HMO-POS plans compete are thus generally
no
larger than the local areas within which HMO and HMO-POS enrollees demand access to
poviders.  More specifically, a small but significant increase in the price of HMO and
HMO-
POS plans would not cause a sufficient number of customers to switch to health plans outside
of
these regions to make such a price increase unprofitable.  For this reason, the Department's
analysis focused on MSAs in and around Houston and Dallas as the relevant geographic
markets.
(Complaint ¶ 20.)c.Competitive Effects
Aetna
and Prudential are among each other's principal competitors in the sale of HMO
and HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas, and employers currently view them as close
substitutes based on product design and quality.  Maintaining Prudential as a competitor to
Aetna
in Houston and Dallas has become particularly important since Aetna's 1998 acquisition of
NYLCare, a transaction that propelled Aetna's HMO and HMO-POS market share from 13%
to
44% in Houston and from 11% to 26% in Dallas.  (Complaint ¶ 22.)  The proposed
acquisition
of Prudential would further enhance Aetna's position by eliminating competition between
the
two companies, giving Aetna market shares of 63% in Houston and 42% in Dallas.3  (Id.)


As
the Complaint alleges, potential or current competitors will not be able to constrain
Aetna's exercise of its post-merger market power in the defined geographic markets.
(Complaint ¶ 25.)  Effective new entry for a HMO or HMO-POS plan in Houston
or
Dallas
typically takes two to three years and costs approximately $50 million.4 
(Complaint ¶ 23.) 
In
such an environment, de novo entry is unlikely to defeat a price increase over the
short term.
(Id.)  Furthermore, companies currently offering PPO or indemnity plans are unlikely
to shift
their resources to provide HMO or HMO-POS plans in Houston or Dallas in the event of a
small
but significant price increase.  A number of managed care providers have stated during
interviews that such a shift would be difficult, expensive, and time consuming, and that
they
would not enter the HMO or HMO-POS markets even if Aetna were to raise its prices a
"small
but significant amount."  (Merger Guidelines ¶ 1.11.)  Finally, managed care
companies
that
presently offer HMO or HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas are unlikely to be able to
expand or reposition themselves sufficiently to restrain anticompetitive behavior by Aetna
in
either area following the transaction.  (Complaint ¶ 24.)  Not only would these
companies face
some of the costs and difficulties of a new entrant, they would be unable to contend
successfully
with Aetna's advantages in national reputation, quality accreditation, product array, and
provider
network. (Id.)  It is therefore unlikely that either new entry or expansion by
competitors could
counteract a post-merger price increase.  (Complaint ¶ 25.)


For
all of these reasons, the proposed transaction would enable the merged entity to
increase prices or reduce the quality of HMO and HMO-POS plans available to consumers
in
these areas, in violation of Section 7.


2.The Purchase of Physicians' Services


As
alleged in the Complaint, Aetna's acquisition of Prudential will also consolidate its
purchasing power over physicians' services in Houston and Dallas, enabling the merged entity
to
unduly reduce the rates paid for those services. 5


a.Product Market


Physicians' services are those medical services provided and sold by
physicians, and the
only purchasers are individual patients or the commercial and government health insurers
that purchase their services on behalf of individual patients.   (Complaint ¶ 27.)  As
a
result,
physicians cannot seek other purchasers in the event of a small but significant decrease in
the
prices paid by these buyers.  (Id.)  Nor will such a price decrease cause physicians to
stop
providing their services or shift towards other activities in numbers sufficient to make such
a
price reduction unprofitable.  (Id.)  Physicians' services thus constitute the relevant
product
market within which to assess the likely effect of Aetna's acquisition of Prudential. 
(Id.)


b.Geographic Markets


The
geographic markets for the purchase and sale of physicians' services are localized.
In Houston and Dallas, as elsewhere, patients seeking medical care generally prefer to
have
access to treatment close to where they work or live.  As a result, commercial and
government
health insurers -- the primary purchasers of physicians' services -- seek to have in their
provider
networks physicians whose offices are convenient to where their enrollees work or live.
(Complaint ¶ 19.)  Consequently, physicians could not shift their services towards
purchasers
outside of these areas in numbers sufficient to make a price reduction unprofitable in the
event
of a small but significant decrease in the prices paid to physicians practicing in Houston or
Dallas.


Furthermore, an established physician who has invested time and expense in
building a
practice in Houston or Dallas (or any other locale) would incur considerable costs in moving
his
or her practice to a new geographic area, including the substantial costs of building new
relationships with hospitals, other physicians, employees, and patients in the new area.
(Complaint ¶ 28.)  For these reasons, a small but significant decrease in the prices
paid
to
physicians practicing in Houston or Dallas would not cause physicians to relocate their
practices
in numbers sufficient to make such a price reduction unprofitable.  (Complaint ¶
29.)
For
all of these reasons, the MSAs in and around Houston and Dallas constitute the
relevant geographic markets.  (Id.; Merger Guidelines ¶ 1.21.)


c.Competitive Effects


In
Houston and Dallas, as elsewhere, the contract terms a physician can obtain from a
managed care company such as Aetna or Prudential depend on the physician's ability to
terminate, or to credibly threaten to terminate, his or her relationship if the company
demands
unfavorable contract terms.  (Complaint ¶ 30.)  Since physicians' services, unlike
certain
tangible products, cannot be stored until the physician finds a more acceptable buyer, failing
to
replace lost business expeditiously imposes an irrevocable loss of revenue upon a physician.
Consequently, a physician's ability to terminate, or credibly threaten to terminate, a
provider
relationship depends on his or her ability to make up that lost business promptly. 
(Id.)


Physicians, however, generally have only a limited ability to encourage
patients to switch
health care plans or providers.  (Complaint ¶ 31.)  To retain a patient after
terminating a
plan
requires the physician to convince the patient either to switch to another employer-sponsored
plan
in which the physician participates (which might not be an option) or to pay considerably
higher
out-of-pocket costs, either in the form of increased copayments for use of an
out-of-network
physician (if allowed) or by absorbing the total cost of the physician's services as
unreimbursed
medical expenses.  As a result, a physician who discontinues his or her relationship with Aetna
could
expect to lose a significant share of his or her Aetna patients.


A
physician's ability to replace, in a timely manner, such lost business is significantly
diminished when a large number of patients need to be replaced.  (Complaint ¶ 32.) 
Because of
Aetna's "all products clause" -- which requires a physician to participate in all of Aetna's
health
plans if he or she participates in any Aetna plan -- a physician would lose patients from all
Aetna
plans if he or she rejects the rates or other terms of any one Aetna plan.  Thus, the cost of
replacing
Aetna patients will be greater when Aetna plans collectively account for a larger share of a
physician's total revenue.


Furthermore, the ability to replace a given
number of Aetna patients is diminished when a
physician's non-Aetna sources of patients are more limited.  Consequently, the cost of
replacing
Aetna patients will be greater the larger Aetna's share of all patients in a locality.


Aetna's proposed acquisition of Prudential, following its recent acquisition of
NYLCare, will
give it control over both a large share of the revenue of a substantial number of physicians
in
Houston and Dallas and a large share of all patients in those areas.  (Complaint ¶
33.)  In
light of
the limited ability of physicians to encourage patient switching, a significantly larger number
of
physicians in Houston and Dallas would be unable to reject Aetna's demands for more
adverse
contract terms if Aetna were allowed to acquire Prudential.  (Id.)  The proposed
acquisition thus
would give Aetna the ability to unduly depress physician reimbursement rates in Houston
and
Dallas, likely leading to a reduction in quantity or degradation in the quality of physicians'
services.
(Id.; see also Merger Guidelines ¶ 0.1.)


III.
EXPLANATION OF THE PROPOSED FINAL
JUDGMENT


The
proposed Final Judgment orders and directs Aetna to divest its interests in the Houston
operations of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and the Dallas operations of NYLCare-Southwest,
consisting
of, among other assets, approximately 260,000 and 167,000 commercially insured HMO and
HMO-POS enrollees in Houston and Dallas, respectively.6  (See Final
Judgment ¶ II.E. and F.)



The
provisions of the proposed Final Judgment are designed to eliminate the two
anticompetitive effects of the proposed acquisition.  First, the divestitures will preserve
competition
and protect consumers from higher prices for HMO and HMO-POS plans by establishing a
new,
independent, and economically viable competitor -- or by significantly strengthening the
existing
competitors -- in the development, marketing, and sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans in
the
Houston and Dallas areas.  Second, the divestitures will prevent the consolidation of
purchasing
power over physicians' services in Houston and Dallas and thereby deny Aetna the ability to
unduly
depress physician reimbursement rates.


In
order to meet these two objectives, the proposed Final Judgment requires that Aetna
promptly make NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest available for purchase. 
(Final
Judgment ¶ IV.D.)  Aetna must give all prospective purchasers reasonable access to
all
NYLCare-
Gulf Coast's and NYLCare-Southwest's personnel, physical facilities, and any and all
financial,
operational, or other documents and information customarily provided as part of a due
diligence
process.  (Final Judgment ¶ IV.E.)  At the same time, Aetna must immediately
cease all
actions
directed at the integration of NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest into Aetna and
must take all steps necessary to ensure that NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are
maintained
and operated as independent, on-going, economically viable, and active competitors.
(Final
Judgment ¶ IV. F. and G.)  Such steps must include the appointment of experienced
senior
management to run NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest until the divestitures
required
by the Final Judgement have been accomplished, as well as the creation of a separate and
independent sales organization, provider relations organization, patient
management/quality
management organization, commercial operations organization, network operations
organization,
and underwriting organization.  (Final Judgment ¶ IV.G.1-7.)  To maintain the
viability
of the
NYLCare entities, Aetna is also required to provide certain support services (i.e., legal,
financial,
actuarial, software, and computer operations support) to NYLCare-Gulf Coast and
NYLCare-
Southwest until the divestitures are completed.  (Final Judgment ¶ IV.G.8.)


The
proposed Final Judgment prohibits Aetna from taking any action to consummate the
proposed acquisition until such time as plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, are satisfied that
NYLCare-Gulf Coast and NYLCare-Southwest are independent and viable competitors and
that
Aetna has complied with the terms of the Hold Separate Stipulation and Order or until the
divestitures required by this Final Judgement are completed.  (Final Judgment ¶
IV.H.)  
The
divestitures must be accomplished by selling or conveying NYLCare-Gulf Coast and
NYLCare-
Southwest to a purchaser(s) in such a way as to satisfy the plaintiffs, in their sole discretion, that
the
entities conveyed can and will be used by the purchaser(s) as part of a viable, ongoing
business
engaged in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas.  (Final Judgment
¶ IV.I.)
The divestitures may be made to one or more purchasers provided that in each instance it
is
demonstrated, to the sole satisfaction of the plaintiffs, that the acquirer(s) will remain
viable
competitors.  (Id.)  The divestitures must be made to a purchaser(s) which is shown, to
the plaintiffs'
sole satisfaction, to have

 the capability and intent of competing effectively in the sale of
HMO
and HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas, 

the managerial, operational, and financial
capability to compete effectively in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans in Houston and
Dallas,
and

 no limitation, through any agreement with Aetna or otherwise, in its ability to
compete
effectively in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS plans in Houston and Dallas.
(Id.)


Aetna
must file all required applications for regulatory approval of the divestitures within
one-hundred twenty (120) calendar days after the date on which the proposed Final Judgment
was
filed (i.e., June 21, 1999) and must complete the divestitures within five (5) business days after
it
receives all necessary regulatory approvals, or five (5) business days after notice of the entry of
this
Final Judgment by the Court, whichever is later.  (Final Judgment ¶ IV.B.)  The
plaintiffs may
extend the time period for the divestitures by no more than sixty (60) calendar days and may,
in
their sole discretion, grant any further time extension needed by Aetna to obtain regulatory
approval
of the divestitures.  (Final Judgment ¶ IV.C.)


If
Aetna cannot accomplish these divestitures within the above-described period, the
proposed Final Judgment provides that, upon application by the plaintiffs, the Court will
appoint
a trustee to effect the divestitures.  (Final Judgment ¶ V.A.)  After the trustee's
appointment
becomes effective, the trustee will file monthly reports with the parties and the Court, setting
forth
the trustee's efforts to accomplish the divestiture.  (Final Judgment ¶ V.E.)  If the
trustee
has not
accomplished such divestitures within six (6) months after its appointment, the trustee and
the
parties will make recommendations to the Court, which shall enter such orders as it deems
appropriate to carry out the purpose of the trust, including, if necessary, extending the trust and
the
term of the trustee's appointment by a period requested by the plaintiffs.  (Final Judgment
¶ V.F.)


The
proposed Final Judgment also requires Aetna to deliver affidavits to plaintiffs as to the
fact and manner of its compliance with the Final Judgment within twenty-five (25) calendar
days
of the Court's June 21, 1999 entry of the Hold Separate Order and Stipulation, and every thirty
(30)
calendar days thereafter, until the divestitures have been completed.  (Final
Judgment ¶
VII.A.)
Aetna must also submit, within twenty-five (25) calendar days of the Court's entry of the
Hold
Separate Order and Stipulation, an affidavit that describes in detail all actions Aetna has taken
and
all steps Aetna has implemented on an on-going basis to preserve NYLCare-Gulf Coast
and
NYLCare-Southwest, describing Aetna's efforts to maintain and operate NYLCare-Gulf Coast
and
NYLCare-Southwest as active competitors, and the plans and timetable for Aetna's integration
of
Prudential's health care assets. (Final Judgment ¶ VII.B.)


The
relief sought has been tailored to safeguard Houston and Dallas consumers from an
increase in price or a reduction in quality of HMO and HMO-POS products.  The relief sought
also
ensures that physicians in these markets will be protected from an undue depression of
reimbursement rates, which could have led to a reduction in the quantity or a degradation in
the
quality of physicians' services.
IV.
REMEDIES AVAILABLE TO
POTENTIAL PRIVATE LITIGANTS


Section 4 of the Clayton Act (15 U.S.C. § 15) provides that any person
who has been injured
as a result of conduct prohibited by the antitrust laws may bring suit in federal court to recover
three
times the damages the person has suffered, as well as costs and reasonable attorney's fees. 
Entry
of the proposed Final Judgment will neither impair nor assist the bringing of any private
antitrust
damage action.  Under the provisions of Section 5(a) of the Clayton Act (15
U.S.C. §
16(a)), entry
of the proposed Final Judgment has no primafacie effect in any subsequent
private lawsuit that may
be brought against Aetna or Prudential.

V.
PROCEDURES AVAILABLE FOR
MODIFICATION OF THE PROPOSED
FINAL JUDGMENT


The
parties have stipulated that the proposed Final Judgment may be entered by the Court
after compliance with the provisions of the APPA, provided that the plaintiffs have not
withdrawn
their consent.  The APPA conditions entry upon the Court's determination that the proposed
Final
Judgment is in the public interest.


The
APPA provides a period of at least sixty (60) days preceding the effective date of the
proposed Final Judgment within which any person may submit to the United States written
comments regarding the proposed Final Judgment.  Any person should comment within sixty
(60)
days of the date this Competitive Impact Statement is published in the Federal Register.  The
United
States will evaluate and respond to the comments.  All comments will be given due
consideration
by the Department of Justice, which remains free to withdraw its consent to the proposed
Final
Judgment at any time prior to entry.  The comments and the response of the United States will
be
filed with the Court and published in the Federal Register.



Written comments should be submitted to:

          Gail Kursh
          Chief, Health Care
Task Force
          Antitrust
Division
          U.S. Department of
Justice
          325 Seventh St., N.W.,
Suite 400
          Washington, D.C. 
20530
The proposed Final Judgment provides that the Court will retain jurisdiction over this action
and
that
the parties may apply to the Court for any order necessary or appropriate for the
modification,
interpretation, or enforcement of the Final Judgment.

VI.
ALTERNATIVES TO THE PROPOSED
FINAL JUDGMENT


The
Department considered, as an alternative to the proposed Final Judgment, a full trial on
the merits of the Complaint against the defendants.  The Department is satisfied, however, that
the
divestitures of the assets and other relief contained in the proposed Final Judgment will
preserve
viable competition in the sale of HMO and HMO-POS products and in the purchase of
physicians'
services in Houston and Dallas, Texas that otherwise would be affected adversely by the
acquisition.
Thus, the proposed Final Judgment
would achieve the relief the Department would have obtained through litigation, but avoids the
time, expense, and uncertainty of a full trial on the merits of the
Complaint.

VII.
STANDARD OF REVIEW
UNDER THE APPA FOR PROPOSED FINAL JUDGMENT


The
APPA requires that proposed consent judgments in antitrust cases brought by the United
States be subject to a sixty (60) day comment period, after which the Court shall determine
whether
entry of the proposed Final Judgment "is in the public interest."  In making that determination,
the
Court may consider:

the competitive impact of such judgment, including termination of alleged
violations, provisions for enforcement and modification, duration of
relief
sought, anticipated effects of alternative remedies actually considered, and
any
other
considerations bearing upon the adequacy of such judgment; [and]

the impact of entry of such judgment upon the public generally and individuals
alleging specific injury from the violations set forth in the complaint
including
consideration of the public benefit, if any, to be derived from a determination
of the
issues at trial.

15 U.S.C. § 16(e).


As
the United States Court of Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit has
held, this statute permits a court to consider, among other things, the relationship
between the remedy secured and the specific allegations set forth in the plaintiff's
Complaint, whether the decree is sufficiently clear, whether enforcement mechanisms
are sufficient, and whether the decree may positively harm third parties.
SeeUnited
States v. Microsoft Corp., 56 F.3d 1448, 1461-62 (D.C. Cir. 1995).  In conducting
this
inquiry, "[t]he Court is nowhere compelled to go to trial or to engage in extended
proceedings which might have the effect of vitiating the benefits of prompt and less
costly settlement through the consent decree process."7  Rather,


[a]bsent a showing of corrupt failure of the government to discharge its
duty,
the Court, in making its public interest finding, should . . .
carefully consider the explanations of the government in the
competitive impact statement and its responses to comments in order to
determine whether those explanations are reasonable under the
circumstances.


United States v. Mid-America Dairymen, Inc., 1977-1 Trade Cas. ¶
61,508 at
71,980
(W.D. Mo. 1977).


Accordingly, with respect to the adequacy of the relief secured by the
decree,
a court may not "engage in an unrestricted evaluation of what relief would best serve
the public." United States v. BNS, Inc., 858 F.2d 456, 462 (9th Cir. 1988)
(citing
United States v. Bechtel Corp., 648 F.2d 660, 666 (9th Cir. 1981)); see
alsoMicrosoft,
56 F.3d at 1460-62.  The law requires that


the
balancing of competing social and political interests affected by a
proposed antitrust consent decree must be left, in the first instance, to
the
discretion of the Attorney General.  The court's role in protecting
the
public interest is one of insuring that the government has not
breached its duty to the public in consenting to the decree.  The court
is
required to determine not whether a particular decree is the one that
will
best serve society, but whether the settlement is "within the reaches
of
the public interest."  More elaborate requirements might undermine
the
effectiveness of antitrust enforcement by consent decree.8


A proposed Final Judgment, therefore, need not eliminate every anticompetitive effect
of a particular practice, nor guarantee free competition in the future.  Court approval
of a final judgment requires a standard more flexible and less strict than the standard
required for a finding of liability:  "[A] proposed decree must be approved even if it
falls short of the remedy the court would impose on its own, as long as it falls within
the range of acceptability or is 'within the reaches of public interest.' "9


The
proposed Final Judgment here offers strong and effective relief that fully
addresses the competitive harm posed by the proposed transaction.

VIII.
DETERMINATIVE DOCUMENTS


There
are no determinative materials or documents of the type described in
Section 2(b) of the APPA, 15 U.S.C. § 16(b), that were considered by the United
States in formulating the proposed Final Judgment.  Consequently, none are filed herewith.

Dated:July 15, 1999


Respectfully submitted,


                                                                 ___________/s/__________
                                                                  PAUL J. O'DONNELL
                                                                  JOHN B. ARNETT, SR.
                                                                  STEVEN BRODSKY
                                                                 DEBORAH A. BROWN
                                                                 CLAUDIA H. DULMAGE
                                                                 DIONNE C. LOMAX
                                                                 FREDERICK S. YOUNG
                                                                 Attorneys
                                                                 U.S. Department of Justice
                                                                 Antitrust Division
                                                                 Health Care Task Force
                                                                 325 Seventh St. N.W., Suite 400
                                                                 Washington, D.C.  20530
                                                                 Tel: (202) 616-5933
                                                                 Facsimile: (202) 514- 1517


FOOTNOTES
1     In the event
plaintiffs are unable to agree on a course of action within seven (7) days, the United States may,
in its sole discretion, act alone (or decline to act) with respect to the relevant course of action. 
(Final Judgment ¶ XII.)
2   Other health
plans,
along with many brokers and consultants, agree, noting the difference in networks, benefits,
regulatory requirements, administrative systems, medical management requirements, and cost of
HMO and HMO-based POS plans as opposed to PPO plans and indemnity coverage.  Indeed,
Aetna's and Prudential's own marketing materials strongly suggest that they view them as
different products as well.
3     The
Department
looked carefully at the various geographic markets around the country where Aetna and
Prudential compete with each other.  In most cases, it determined that Aetna's share of the HMO
and HMO-POS market following the transaction did not raise competitive concerns. Depending
on the MSA, this was because Prudential was not a significant competitor in the area and the
acquisition would add little, if anything, to Aetna's market power, because Aetna itself was too
insignificant a competitor to warrant concern, or because there were significant remaining
competitors such that the acquisition would not likely harm competition.  In contrast, the
proposed transaction would significantly increase Aetna's share of the HMO and HMO-POS
market in Houston and Dallas, and neither entry nor expansion would prevent Aetna from
profitably increasing its prices in these areas.
4   Indeed,
Aetna has
acknowledged that on average it costs between $600 and $1000 per enrollee to build
membership in a HMO.
5     Section 7
prohibits mergers or acquisitions that are likely to lessen competition or tend to create a
monopoly in the purchase, as well as the sale, of any line of commerce in any area of the
country. See U.S. v. Syufy Enters., 903 F. 2d 659, 663 (9th Cir.
1990);  U.S. v. Rice Growers Ass'n, 1986-2 Trade Cases ¶ 67,288 (E.D. Cal.
1986);
U.S. v. Pennzoil Co., 252 F. Supp. 962 (W.D. Pa. 1965); see generally R. Blair & J.
Harrison, Monopsony 81-84 (1993).
6     The
proposed
Final Judgment requires the divestiture of certain NYLCare assets rather than certain Prudential
assets because of the legal and regulatory difficulties of divesting Prudential's Houston and
Dallas HMO and HMO-POS businesses.  However, the required divestiture of NYLCare's
business will have an effect comparable to the divestiture of Prudential's business in these areas. 
Prudential has approximately 172,400 HMO and HMO-POS enrollees in the Houston area, while
the proposed Final Judgment requires Aetna to divest approximately 260,000 NYLCare
enrollees in that area.  In Dallas, Prudential has approximately 171,000 HMO and HMO-POS
enrollees. The proposed Final Judgment requires Aetna to divest approximately 167,000
NYLCare enrollees there.
7
 
119 Cong. Rec. 24598 (1973).  See United States v. Gillette Co., 406 F. Supp. 713,
715 (D. Mass. 1975).  A "public interest" determination can be made properly on the basis of the
Competitive Impact Statement and Response to Comments filed pursuant to the APPA. 
Although the APPA authorizes the use of additional procedures, 15 U.S.C. § 16(f),
those
procedures are discretionary.  A court need not invoke any of them unless it believes that the
comments have raised significant issues and that further proceedings would aid the court in
resolving those issues.  See H.R. Rep. 93-1463, 93rd Cong. 2d Sess. 8-9 (1974), reprinted
in 1974 U.S.C.C.A.N. 6535, 6538.
8
 
Bechtel, 648 F.2d at 666 (citations omitted) (emphasis added); see BNS, 858
F.2d at 463;  United States v. National Broad. Co., 449 F. Supp. 1127, 1143 (C.D. Cal.
1978); Gillette, 406 F. Supp. at 716.  See also Microsoft, 56 F.3d at 1461
(whether "the remedies [obtained in the decree are] so inconsonant with the allegations charged
as to fall outside of the 'reaches of the public interest' ") (citations omitted).
9
 
United States v. American Tel. and Tel. Co., 552 F. Supp. 131, 151 (D.D.C. 1982), aff'd.
sub nom. Maryland v. United States, 460 U.S. 1001 (1983) (quoting Gillette
Co., 406 F. Supp. at 716 (citations omitted)); United States v. Alcan Aluminum, Ltd.,
605 F. Supp. 619, 622 (W.D. Ky. 1985).




 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    