
    <document>
        <title>Stipulation</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Aetna and The Prudential Insurance 
            Company</case_name>
        <text>




This document is available 
        in two formats: this web page (for browsing content) and PDF 
        (comparable to original document formatting). To view the PDF you will 
        need Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe 
        site. For an official signed copy, please contact the Antitrust 
        Documents Group. 







                   UNITED
STATES DISTRICT COURT
FOR THE NORTHERN DISTRICT OF TEXAS
(DALLAS DIVISION)







UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, and the           				
STATE OF TEXAS,               
           
Plaintiffs,


            
                v.    

AETNA INC., and									
THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE COMPANY OF AMERICA,
            
                           
Defendants.




	    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


Civil Action No.: 3-99 CV 398-H

Filed: June 21, 1999
                 

    





  STIPULATION
It is stipulated by and between the undersigned parties, by their respective attorneys, as
follows:
(1)  This Court has jurisdiction over the subject matter of this action and over each of the
parties hereto, and venue is proper in this Court.
(2) The proposed 
Final Judgment attached hereto may be filed and
entered by the Court, upon the motion of any party or upon the Court's own motion, at any time
after compliance with the requirements of the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. §
16, and without further notice to any party or other proceedings, provided that the plaintiffs have
not withdrawn their consent, which it may do at any time before entry of the proposed Final
Judgment by serving notice thereof on all other parties and by filing that notice with the Court.
(3)  Defendants shall abide by and comply with the provisions of the proposed Final
Judgment pending entry of the Final Judgment by the Court, or until expiration of time for all
appeals of any Court ruling declining entry of the proposed Final Judgment, and shall, from the
date of the signing of this Stipulation, comply with all the terms and provisions of the proposed
Final Judgment as though the same were in full force and effect as an order of the Court.
(4)  This Stipulation shall apply with equal force and effect to any amended proposed Final
Judgment agreed upon in writing by the parties and submitted to the Court.
(5)  In the event the plaintiffs withdraw their consent, as provided in paragraph (2) above, or
in the event that the Court declines to enter the proposed Final Judgment pursuant to this
Stipulation, the time has expired for all appeals of any Court ruling declining entry of the
proposed Final Judgment, and the Court has not otherwise ordered continued compliance with
the terms and provisions of the proposed Final Judgment, then the parties are released from all
further obligations under this Stipulation, and the making of this Stipulation shall be without
prejudice to any party in this or any other proceeding.
(6)  Defendants represent that the divestitures ordered in the proposed Final Judgment can
and will be made, and that defendants will later raise no claims of hardship or difficulty as
grounds for asking the Court to modify any of the divestiture provisions contained therein.

Dated:    June 21, 1999

Respectfully submitted,



FOR PLAINTIFF
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA               
                

__________/s/__________
PAUL J. O'DONNELL
Massachusetts Bar #547125
U.S. Department of Justice
Antitrust Division
Health Care Task Force
325 Seventh Street, N.W., Suite 400
Washington, D.C. 20530
Tel: (202) 616-5933
Facsimile: (202) 514-1517


FOR PLAINTIFF
STATE OF TEXAS

__________/s/__________
MARK TOBEY
Assistant Attorney General
Chief, Antitrust Section
State Bar No. 20082960
Office of the Attorney General
P. O. Box 12548
Austin, Texas  78711-2548
Tel: (512) 463-2185
Facsimile (512) 320-0975
FOR DEFENDANT
AETNA INC.
__________/s/__________
ROBERT E. BLOCH
D.C. Bar #175927
Mayer, Brown & Platt
1909 K Street, N.W.
Washington, D.C. 20006
Tel: (202) 263-3203
Facsimile: (202) 263-3300


FOR DEFENDANT
THE PRUDENTIAL INSURANCE
COMPANY OF AMERICA

__________/s/__________
MICHAEL L. WEINER
Skadden, Arps, Slate, Meagher & Flom, LLP
New York Bar #MW0294
919 Third Avenue
New York, NY 10022
Tel: (212) 735-2632
Facsimile: (212) 451-7446








 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    