
    <document>
        <title>Asset Preservation Stipulation and
[Proposed] Order</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in three
formats: this web page (for browsing content), PDF (comparable to original document formatting), and 
 WordPerfect. To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 








THE UNITED STATES DISTRICT COURTFOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA






UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,    
         
       
Plaintiff,

            
                v. 

ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and    
BOWATER INCORPORATED,
         
       
 Defendants.




    |
    |
    |
    |  
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |
    |          


CASE NO.:


JUDGE:


DECK TYPE: Antitrust


DATE STAMPED:
    


ASSET PRESERVATION STIPULATION AND ORDER
	It is hereby stipulated and agreed by and between the undersigned parties, subject to 
approval and entry by the Court, that: 

I.  DEFINITIONS
	As used in this Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order: 

	A.	"Acquirer" means the entity or entities to whom Defendants divest some or all of 
the Divestiture Assets. 

	B.	"Abitibi" means Defendant Abitibi-Consolidated Inc., a Canadian corporation with 
its headquarters in Montréal, Quebec, Canada, its successors and assigns, and its subsidiaries,
divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships and joint ventures, and their directors, officers,
managers, agents, and employees.

	C.	"Bowater" means Defendant Bowater Incorporated, a Delaware corporation with its
headquarters in Greenville, South Carolina, its successors and assigns, and its subsidiaries, 
divisions, groups, affiliates, partnerships and joint ventures, and their directors, officers,
managers, agents, and employees. 

	D.	"Newsprint" means the lowest grade of uncoated groundwood paper (i.e., paper
manufactured from mechanically processed pulp), regardless of its basis weight.  It is primarily
used in the production of newspapers, but also used in some advertising inserts, comic books,
trade publications, and direct mail, among other end-use products. 

	E.	"Divestiture Assets" means:

	Abitibi's Snowflake, Arizona newsprint mill, located at Spur 277 North, 
Snowflake, Arizona 85937;

	all tangible assets used in the mill listed in Section I(E)(1), including all 
assets relating to research and development activities, manufacturing
equipment, tooling and fixed assets, real property (leased or owned),
personal property, inventory, newsprint reserves, office furniture,
materials, supplies, docking facilities, on- or off-site warehouses or storage
facilities relating to the mill, Apache Railway Company assets; all
licenses, permits and authorizations issued by any governmental
organization relating to the mill; all contracts, agreements, leases
(including renewal rights), commitments, certifications, and
understandings relating to the mill, including supply agreements; all
customer lists, contracts, accounts, and credit records relating to the mill;
all interests in, and contracts relating to, power generation; all repair and
performance records and all other records relating to the mill; and       

	all intangible assets used in the development, production, servicing, 
distribution, and sales of products by the mill listed in Section
I(E)(1),including but 	          not limited to all contractual rights, patents, licenses
and sublicenses, intellectual property, technical information, computer
software and related documentation, know-how, trade secrets, drawings,
blueprints, designs, design protocols, specifications for materials,
specifications for parts and devices, safety procedures for the handling of
materials and substances, quality assurance and control procedures, design
tools and simulation capability, all manuals and technical information
provided to the employees, customers, suppliers, agents or licensees, and
all research data concerning historic and current research and development
efforts relating to the mill, including, but not limited to designs of
experiments, and the results of successful and unsuccessful designs and
experiments. 
II.  OBJECTIVES 
	The proposed Final Judgment filed in this case is meant to ensure Defendants' prompt 

divestiture of the Divestiture Assets for the purpose of establishing a viable competitor in the 

market for the production and sale of newsprint in North America in order to remedy the 

anticompetitive effects that the United States alleges would otherwise result from the 

Defendants' merger.  This Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order ensures that until the 

divestitures required by the proposed Final Judgment have been accomplished, the Divestiture 

Assets remain as an economically viable, competitive, and ongoing business concern.



III.  JURISDICTION AND VENUE
	This Court has jurisdiction over the subject matter of this action, and Defendants 

waive all objections to the Court's exercise of personal jurisdiction over Defendants in this 

action and to the propriety of venue in the United States District Court for the District of 

Columbia.

IV.  COMPLIANCE WITH AND ENTRY OF THE PROPOSED FINAL JUDGMENT
	A.	The parties stipulate that a proposed Final Judgment in the form attached hereto as 

Exhibit A may be filed with and entered by the Court, upon the motion of any party or upon the 

Court's own motion, at any time after compliance with the requirements of the Antitrust 

Procedures and Penalties Act, 15 U.S.C. § 16, and without further notice to any party or other 

proceedings, provided that the United States has not withdrawn its consent, which it may do at 

any time before the entry of the proposed Final Judgment by serving notice thereof on
Defendants and by filing that notice with the Court. 

	B.	Defendants shall abide by and comply with the provisions of the proposed Final 

Judgment, pending the proposed Final Judgment's entry by the Court, or until expiration of time 

for all appeals of any Court ruling declining entry of the proposed Final Judgment, and shall, 

from the date of the signing of this Stipulation by the parties, comply with all the terms and 

provisions of the proposed Final Judgment as though the same were in full force and effect as an 

order of the Court. 

	C.	Defendants shall not consummate the transaction sought to be enjoined by the 

Complaint herein before the Court has signed this Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order. 

	D.	This Stipulation shall apply with equal force and effect to any amended proposed 

Final Judgment agreed upon in writing by the parties and submitted to the Court. 

	E.	In the event: 

 the United States has withdrawn its consent, as provided in Section IV(A) 

above, or 

	the proposed Final Judgment is not entered pursuant to this Stipulation, the 

			time has expired for all appeals of any Court ruling declining entry of the 

			proposed Final Judgment, and the Court has not otherwise ordered 

			continued compliance with the terms and provisions of the proposed Final 

			Judgment, 

then the parties are released from all further obligations under this Stipulation, and the making of 

this Stipulation shall be without prejudice to any party in this or any other proceeding. 
	F.	Defendants represent that the divestitures ordered in the proposed Final Judgment 

can and will be made, and that Defendants will later raise no claim of mistake, hardship, or 

difficulty of compliance as grounds for asking the Court to modify any of the provisions 

contained therein. 

V.  ASSET PRESERVATION PROVISIONS
	Until the divestitures required by the proposed Final Judgment have been accomplished: 

	A.	Defendants shall take all steps necessary to preserve, maintain, and continue to 

operate the Divestiture Assets as an economically viable, competitive, and ongoing business.  

Within twenty (20) days after the entry of the Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order, 

Defendants will inform the United States of the steps Defendants have taken to comply with this 

Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order.

	B.	Defendants shall use their best efforts to maintain and increase the sales and 

revenues of the products produced by or sold by the Divestiture Assets, and shall maintain at 

2007 or previously approved levels for 2008, whichever are higher, all promotional, advertising,
sales, technical assistance, marketing, and merchandising support for the Divestiture Assets. 

	C.	Defendants shall provide sufficient working capital and lines and sources of credit 

to continue to maintain the Divestiture Assets as an economically viable, competitive, and 

ongoing business, consistent with the requirements of Section V(A). 

	D.	Defendants shall take all steps necessary to ensure that the Divestiture Assets are 

fully maintained in operable condition at no less than current capacity and sales levels, and shall 

maintain and adhere to all normal repair and maintenance schedules for the Divestiture Assets.
Further, Defendants shall make all investments and capital expenditures scheduled as of July 1,
2007.

	E.	Defendants shall not, except as part of a divestiture approved by the United States 

in accordance with the terms of the proposed Final Judgment, remove, sell, lease, assign, 

transfer, pledge, or otherwise dispose of any of the Divestiture Assets. 

	F.	Defendants shall use their best efforts to preserve the existing relationships with 

each of the Divestiture Assets' suppliers, customers, and others having business relations with 

the Divestiture Assets, in the ordinary course of the Divestiture Assets' business and in 

accordance with past practice. 

	G.	Defendants' employees with primary responsibility for the production, operation, 

distribution, and sale of the products sold by the Divestiture Assets, shall not be transferred or 

reassigned to other areas within the company except for transfer bids initiated by employees 

pursuant to Defendants' regular, established job posting policy.  Defendants shall provide the 

United States with ten (10) calendar days notice of any such transfer. 

	H.	Defendants shall take no action that would jeopardize, delay, or impede the sale of
the Divestiture Assets. 

	I.	Defendants shall maintain, in accordance with sound accounting principles, 

separate, accurate and complete financial ledgers, books and records that report on a periodic 

basis, such as the last business day of every month, consistent with past practices, the assets, 

liabilities, expenses, revenues and income of the Divestiture Assets. 

	J.	For the period from the date of the filing of the Complaint in this matter until one
(1) year after the sale of the Divestiture Assets, Defendants shall make available and deliver to
the Divestiture Assets within seven (7) business days the spare ceramic center roll from Abitibi's
Thorold, Ontario newsprint mill if: (a) the Acquirer or the person identified in Section V(K),
whomever is in control of the Divestiture Assets at the time, determines that the Divestiture
Assets' PM 3 machine requires a new ceramic center roll and (b) the Divestiture Assets'
permanent spare ceramic center roll, which has already been ordered, has not been delivered.  If
Defendants become obligated to deliver the spare ceramic center roll, then they may identify a
suitable alternative ceramic center roll and request permission from the United States, in its sole
discretion, to deliver the alternative center roll to the Divestiture Assets in place of the Thorold
center roll.  Such permission must be in writing.  In any event, Defendants must deliver the
Thorold center roll or an approved substitute to the Divestiture Assets within seven (7) business
days of being notified of the need for the Thorold roll.  Defendants will no longer be obligated to
provide a ceramic center roll to the Divestiture Assets if either of the ceramic center rolls in
Thorold's PM 6 or PM 7 machines break before the Divestiture Assets require a new ceramic
center roll.

	K.	Pierre Rougeau shall have managerial responsibility for and shall oversee the
Divestiture Assets, subject to the provisions of the proposed Final Judgment.  In the event Mr.
Rougeau is unable to perform his duties, William Harvey shall replace Mr. Rougeau and assume
his duties.  In the event that Mr. Harvey is unable to perform his duties, Defendants shall appoint,
subject to the approval of the United States, a replacement within ten (10) working days.  Should
Defendants fail to appoint a replacement acceptable to the United States within this time period,
the United States shall appoint a replacement. 

	L.	Defendants shall take no action that would interfere with the ability of any trustee 

appointed pursuant to the proposed Final Judgment to complete the divestitures pursuant to the 

proposed Final Judgment to a Acquirer acceptable to the United States. 


M.	This Asset Preservation Stipulation and Order shall remain in effect until 

consummation of the divestitures required by the proposed Final Judgment or until further order 

of the Court. 

Dated: October 23, 2007





   
     
                              Respectfully submitted,





FOR PLAINTIFF 
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA 
   _______________/s/________________ Karl D. Knutsen, Esq.

United States Department of Justice

Antitrust Division, Litigation I Section

1401 H Street, NW, Suite 4000

Washington, DC 20530

(202) 514-0976 
     
 
FOR DEFENDANT 
ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. 
   _______________/s/________________Joseph J. Simons, Esq.

Paul, Weiss, Rifkind, Wharton & Garrison LLP

1615 L Street, NW, Suite 1300

Washington, DC 20036-5694

(202) 223-7370

FOR DEFENDANT
BOWATER INCORPORATED

_______________/s/________________R. Hewitt Pate, Esq.

Hunton & Williams

1900 K Street, NW

Washington, DC 20006

(202) 955-1921




ORDER 
IT IS SO ORDERED by the Court, this ____ day of __________, 2007. 



 


 
 

   _______________________________United States District Judge






 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    