
    <document>
        <title>Memorandum Opinion</title>
        <case_name>U.S. v. Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and 
            Bowater Incorporated</case_name>
        <text>



This document is available in two
formats: this web page (for browsing content) and PDF (comparable to original document formatting). To view the PDF you will need 
Acrobat Reader, which may be downloaded from the Adobe site.  For an official signed copy, please contact the 
Antitrust Documents Group. 
 









UNITED STATES DISTRICT
          COURT FOR THE DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA








UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,     
                  
                Plaintiff, 
                   
                v. 
              
 ABITIBI-CONSOLIDATED INC. and   
                BOWATER INCORPORATED, 
                  
                Defendants. 



 )
			)
              )
              )
              )
             
              )
              )
              )
              )
              )
              )
              )
              )          

 Civil Action No. 07-1912 (RMC) 
 Filed: 11/06/2008 






 MEMORANDUM OPINION 

Pursuant to Section 2(e)-(f) of the Antitrust Procedures and Penalties 
          Act (the "Tunney Act"), 15 U.S.C. § 16(e)-(f), and with the consent 
          of the Defendants, the United States moved for entry of a proposed Final 
          Judgment in this civil antitrust action. The Newspaper Association of 
          America (the "Association") filed a memorandum opposing entry of the 
          proposed Final Judgment.1 After consideration 
          of the parties' briefs and the full record, the Court finds that the 
          United States has shown that the proposed Final Judgment is in the public 
          interest and will enter it accordingly. 
        I. BACKGROUND
Abitibi-Consolidated Inc. and Bowater Incorporated were the two largest 
          newsprint producers in North America when they announced their plan 
          to merge. The Department of Justice, on behalf of the United States, 
          challenged the merger alleging that it would violate Section 7 of the 
          Clayton Act, 15 U.S.C. § 18, but then agreed to settle the case 
          with a consent decree, as reflected in the proposed Final Judgment. 
          The proposed decree required the merged firm to divest a newsprint mill 
          in Snowflake, Arizona. Abitibi and Bowater consummated their merger 
          and divested the mill. 
        Simultaneously with filing its motion, the United States filed a Certificate 
          of Compliance certifying that the parties have complied with the provisions 
          of the Tunney Act and that the waiting periods imposed by the Tunney 
          Act have expired.2 Notice of the proposed 
          Final Judgment was published in the Federal Register on November 8, 
          2007. Thus, the sixty-day comment period ended on February 7, 2008. 
          Notice of the proposed Final Judgment was published in a local newspaper, 
          The Washington Post, starting on November 18, 2007, and ending 
          on November 24, 2007. The United States received one comment; a twenty-two-page 
          document with over two- hundred pages of attachments, from the Association 
          on January 2, 2008. The United States responded to this comment on April 
          18, 2008, and published the Association's comment, its attachments, 
          and the response of the United States in the Federal Register on June 
          10, 2008.3 See 15 U.S.C. § 
          16(d) (the United States shall file comments with the district court 
          and publish them in the Federal Register). 
        II. STANDARD OF REVIEW
Both sides agree that the standard of review of the proposed Final 
          Judgment is whether it is in the public interest. The Tunney Act provides 
          in relevant part: 
        

 Before entering any consent judgment proposed by the United States 
              under this section, the court shall determine that the entry of 
              such judgment is in the public interest. For the purpose of such 
              determination, the court shall consider – 

the competitive impact of such judgment, including termination 
                  of alleged violations, provisions for enforcement and modification, 
                  duration of relief sought, anticipated effects of alternative 
                  remedies actually considered, whether its terms are ambiguous, 
                  and any other competitive considerations bearing upon the adequacy 
                  of such judgment that the court deems necessary to a determination 
                  of whether the consent judgment is in the public interest; and
 the impact of entry of such judgment upon competition in 
                  the relevant market or markets, upon the public generally and 
                  individuals alleging specific injury from the violations set 
                  forth in the complaint including consideration of the public 
                  benefit, if any, to be derived from a determination of the issues 
                  at trial. 




15 U.S.C. § 16(e)(1). The proposed Final Judgment "must be approved 
          even if it falls short of the remedy the court would impose on its own, 
          as long as it falls within the range of acceptability or is within the 
          reaches of the public interest." United States v. American Tel. 
          & Tel. Co., 552 F. Supp. 131, 151 (D.D.C. 1982) (quotation 
          marks and citation omitted). The Court "is not permitted to reject the 
          proposed remedies merely because the court believes other remedies are 
          preferable." United States v. SBC Commc'ns, Inc., 489 F. Supp. 
          2d 1, 15 (D.D.C. 2007) (citing United States v. Microsoft Corp., 
          56 F.3d 1448, 1460 (D.C. Cir. 1995)). " Accordingly, the relevant inquiry 
          is whether there is a factual foundation for the government's decisions 
          such that its conclusions regarding the proposed settlement are reasonable." 
          Id. at 15-16 (citing Microsoft, 56 F.3d at 1461); 
          see also United States v. AT&T Inc., 541 F. Supp. 2d 2, 
          6-7 (D.D.C. 2008) (same). "The government need not prove that the settlements 
          will perfectly remedy the alleged antitrust harms, it need only provide 
          a factual basis for concluding that the settlements are reasonably adequate 
          remedies for the alleged harms." SBC Commc'ns, 489 F. Supp. 
          2d at 17. 
        III. ANALYSIS
In this case, whether the settlement is in the public interest depends 
          on the adequacy of the divestiture of the Snowflake newsprint mill. 
          If there is a factual basis for concluding that the divestiture is a 
          reasonably adequate remedy for the harm predicted in the Complaint, 
          then the settlement should be approved. If there is not, then the settlement 
          should be rejected. Thus, the starting point is identifying the harm 
          predicted in the Complaint. 
        The Complaint alleges that although declining demand for newsprint 
          over time will cause newsprint producers to curtail production and reduce 
          capacity, the combination of Abitibi's and Bowater's large market shares 
          will provide the merged firm with the incentive and ability to close 
          capacity sooner than either firm otherwise would absent the merger and 
          to raise prices and profit from the higher margins on the merged firm's 
          remaining capacity. Compl. ¶¶ 17-19. As the United States 
          explained in its Competitive Impact Statement ("CIS"), "if Defendants 
          were allowed to merge without a divestiture, the merged firm would be 
          able to close its capacity strategically, allowing the merged firm to 
          raise newsprint prices and recoup its lost profits on its combined output." 
          CIS at 9. The issue, then, is whether the United States has provided 
          a factual basis for concluding that divestiture of the Snowflake newsprint 
          mill is reasonably likely to "reduce the capacity over which the merged 
          firm could profit to a level at which it would not have the ability 
          to close capacity strategically." Id.
The Court finds that the United States has provided such a factual 
          basis. In support of its conclusion that divestiture of the Snowflake 
          mill will adequately remedy the harms identified in the Complaint, the 
          United States submitted the Declaration of Nicholas Hill, an economist 
          at the Antitrust Division of the United States Department of Justice. 
          See Pl.'s Reply in Supp. of Mot. for Final J., Ex. 1 (Decl. 
          of Nicholas Hill ("Hill Decl.")). Mr. Hill explained that the United 
          States analyzed the merger using an approach called the capacity closure 
          method.4 Id. ¶ 9. Inputting 
          data obtained for all of the mills owned by the Defendants, the United 
          States analyzed the merger using the capacity closure method. Id. 
          ¶ 10. That analysis showed that the Defendants would close 
          a number of unprofitable mills irrespective of the merger. Id. It 
          also showed that the merger would give the merged company an incentive 
          to close some profitable mills that the individual firms would not close 
          absent the merger. Id. ¶ 11. Therefore, the United States 
          evaluated whether the incentive to close profitable capacity could be 
          eliminated through divestiture. Id. The United States did that 
          by running the capacity closure method analysis many times, each time 
          assuming that the merged company had divested a different set of mills. 
          Id. That process identified all of the divestitures that removed 
          the merged firm's incentive to close profitable capacity. Id. The 
          United States selected the Snowflake mill among the mills identified 
          because, unlike some of the other candidates, the Snowflake mill was 
          highly efficient and would remain profitable for the foreseeable future. 
          Id. Based on the results of its capacity closure method analysis, 
          the United States concluded that divesting the Snowflake mill would 
          sufficiently reduce the merged firm's incentive to close capacity strategically. 
          See CIS at 7-8. 
        The Association disputes this conclusion. It argues that the Snowflake 
          divestiture is too small to deter the merged firm from closing capacity 
          strategically. In support of its hypothesis that the Snowflake divestiture 
          is inadequate to remedy the harms alleged in the Complaint, the Association 
          points to the fact that the merged firm has reduced capacity and increased 
          prices since the merger and divestiture. However, the mills that the 
          merged firm closed were unprofitable, a fact confirmed by the United 
          States after reviewing the merged firm's confidential profit and loss 
          statements at these mills.5 See Hill 
          Decl. ¶ 25. In addition, real newsprint prices, which account for 
          cost inflation, are lower than they were pre-merger. See id. ¶ 
          15. 
        In any event, the relevant inquiry is whether the United States' conclusion 
          about the adequacy of the Snowflake divestiture was reasonable, not 
          whether it was correct. SBC Commc'ns, 489 F. Supp. 2d at 15-17. 
          The United States has provided a factual basis for concluding that the 
          Snowflake divestiture was reasonably adequate to eliminate the merged 
          firm's incentive to close capacity strategically. Irrespective of whether 
          that conclusion were correct, the United States has established an "ample 
          foundation for [its] judgment call" and thus shown "its conclusion [was] 
          reasonable." Microsoft, 56 F.3d at 1461. 
       
        IV. CONCLUSION
For the foregoing reasons the Court finds that the divestiture of the 
          Snowflake mill is a reasonably adequate remedy for the harm predicted 
          in the Complaint. Accordingly, the Court will approve the proposed Final 
          Judgment as being within the public interest. The Final Judgment accompanies 
          this Memorandum Opinion. 



 Date: November 5, 2008

 _______________/s/________________
              ROSEMARY M. COLLYER 
              United States District Judge 




FOOTNOTES

1 By order dated June 5, 2008, the Court 
          permitted the Association to appear as amicus curiae. 
        2 The Tunney Act prescribes a sixty-day 
          period following publication of notice in the Federal Register that 
          a settlement has been reached for the submission of comments. 15 U.S.C. 
          §§ 16(b) & (d). The Tunney Act also prescribes a sixty-day 
          waiting period following commencement of publication in a local newspaper 
          before a proposed final judgment may be entered. Id. § 
          16(c). 
        3 In its brief, the United States qualifies 
          a statement made in the June 10, 2008, Federal Register publication: 
        
As an example of swings in pricing based on changes in input costs 
            and industry capacity, the United States stated that newsprint prices 
            were at or below the lowest level which prices reached in 2006. Response 
            of Plaintiff United States to Public Comments on the Proposed Final 
            Judgment, at 11-15. That statement was made based on industry information 
            available as of the date of the filing. Since that filing, data released 
            for the entire month of April indicate that the average newsprint 
            prices for April 2008 were one to two percent higher than they were 
            at the lowest point of 2006. 

Pl.'s Mem. in Supp. of Final J., at 2 n.1. 
        4 Under the capacity closure method, it 
          is assumed that a firm will raise prices by closing otherwise profitable 
          capacity. Hill Decl. ¶ 9. A firm's incentive to close profitable 
          capacity is measured by calculating its profit under every possible 
          set of capacity closures that it could undertake. Id. A firm's 
          profit under the most profitable set of capacity closures is then compared 
          to its current profit. Id. A firm will choose to close profitable 
          capacity only if doing so yields a greater profit than it currently 
          earns. Id.
5 There is no basis for the Court to question 
          the United States' characterization of the confidential information 
          on which it relied. If the Court were to require the United States to 
          disclose such confidential information to third parties for verification, 
          companies would be less likely to cooperate with civil investigative 
          demands, frustrating the statutory policy. See 15 U.S.C. § 
          1312. 
        
      



 
var gaJsHost = (("https:" == document.location.protocol) ? "https://ssl." : "http://www."); 
document.write(unescape("%3Cscript src='" + gaJsHost + "google-analytics.com/ga.js' type='text/javascript'%3E%3C/script%3E")); 

 
  try { 
      var pageTracker = _gat._getTracker("UA-36735731-1"); 
      pageTracker._trackPageview(); 
  } catch(err) {}


</text>
    </document>
    